music
music
Our protagonist today Qiu Wenda Director Qiu
我們今天的主角人邱文達邱署長
and ladies and gentlemen
還有各位女士 各位先生
And colleagues in our hospital
還有我們院內的同仁
Goodnight everybody
大家晚安
very happy today
今天很高興喔
we are also we have great honor
我們也是我們有很大的榮幸
Can invite us to Taiwan
能夠請到我們台灣
The Great Patriarch of the Healthcare Industry
衛生醫療界的大家長
Director Qiu Wenda Qiu
邱文達邱署長
Come tell us about his 25 years
來跟我們講他這25年來
research done on neurotrauma
有關於神經創傷所做的研究
Director Qiu Wenda in the United States
邱文達署長在美國
University of Pizza Earns Ph.D.
披薩大學取得博士學位
Also at Nihon University's School of Medicine
也在日本大學的醫學院
PhD in Neurology
取得神經學的博士
Then he was at Taipei Medical University
然後他在台北醫學大學
served many important
曾經擔任過很多重要的
Administrative portfolio includes Director of Neurosurgery
行政組合包括神經外科的主任
Head of Department of Public Health
公衛系的系主任
Director of the Injury Prevention Institute
傷害防治研究所的所長
Taipei Medical University
也擔任台北醫學大學
Vice President of Hospital
副社醫院的院長
Then the vice-principal and the principal
然後副校長跟校長
Director Qiu is also a professor of Doctoral Program in Neurological Disorders
邱署長也是神經災身博士學程的教授
and the director of the Center of Excellence in Clinical Research
還有卓越臨床研究中心的主任
everybody knows
大家都知道
The Department of Health's job is not a good job to do
衛生署的工作不是很好做的工作
But Director Qiu was recruited by the government in 2011
但是邱署長在2011年獲得政府的徵招
As the Director of the Department of Health, it has been quite smooth so far
出任衛生署署長到現在為止做的相當的平穩
Compared with the previous directors, they have done a good job
比起前幾任的署長做得很好
and we thank him
而且我們很謝謝他
Our health depends on his protection
我們的健康都是要靠他的保護
In addition to doing some academic administrative work, Director Qiu
邱署長除了擔任一些學術行政的工作以外
He is also in academic research
他也是在學術研究上
A well-known leading scholar in neurotrauma research at home and abroad
一個國內外知名的神經創傷學研究的領先學者
He once served as the chairman of four important medical associations in China
他曾經擔任過國內四個很重要的醫學會理事長
Society of Surgeons and Neurosurgery
包括外科醫學會神經外科醫學會
Neurotrauma and Injury Prevention
神經創傷以及傷害預防
These are the presidents and directors of the largest medical associations in China.
這都是國內很大的醫學會的會長的理事長
that's not easy
那這是相當不容易的
He has also served as the president of three international associations
他也擔任過三個國際學會的理事長
and Secretary General of the Neurotrauma Committee of the World Association of Neurosurgery
以及世界神經外科醫學會神經創傷委員會的秘書長
And participated in the editing of five international journals
並且參加五個國際期刊的編輯
And he is also a new publisher of an international journal
而且他本人也是一個國際期刊的發新人
So everyone knows this one
所以大家都曉得這一個
Qiu Shuchang is actually very careful in taking care of patients
邱書長實際上他照顧病人很細心
Caring for patients and giving them a lot of love
很關心病人給他們很多的關愛以外
Also doing quite well in academic research
在學術研究上也做得相當好
And more outstanding in academic administration
而且在學術行政上更傑出
So we have a scholar like this
所以我們有這樣的一個學者
to serve as Director of the Department of Health
來擔任衛生署的署長
It is the blessing of our people, really
就是我們全民的福氣 真的是
I have also known Qiu Shuchang for many years
本人也認識邱書長多年
I also admire his academic achievements.
也很仰慕他在學術上的一個成就
Qiu Shuchang made a great contribution to Taiwan
邱書長對台灣有一個很大的貢獻
We say you only need to save one life
我們說你只要救了一個人的命
you can go to heaven
就可以上天堂了
Qiu Shuchang not only saved one life
邱書長不只救一個人命
He killed more than 3,000 people a year
他一年就三千多個人的命
so he's going to heaven now
所以他現在要上好多個天堂
This, Director Zhuo, has been independent all his life in the legislation that motor vehicles are grinders with helmets
這個 卓處長他一生自立於機動車就是磨豆車的帶安全帽的立法
Everyone knows that accidents were the third leading cause of death in Taiwan
那大家都曉得以前事故傷害在台灣是佔第三大死因
That's quite a lot of deaths
那死亡的人數相當的多
Then every time we see a very young person
那我們每次看到一個很年輕的人
Sudden injury from a motor vehicle, then brain trauma and death
忽然有機動車的這個傷害 然後呢腦創傷就死掉
The family is having a hard time and then his siblings are having a hard time
家庭都很難過 然後呢他的兄弟姐妹都很難過
But the best way to prevent this is to wear this helmet
可是這個預防的方法最好的就是帶這個安全帽
As for Director Zhuo, it is actually not easy to promote this activity.
那卓處長呢很 其實在推動這個活動不簡單
Need to have good academic research results
需要有很好的學術研究的成果
And you have to be very determined to join the so-called social movement
而且呢要有很大的決心投入所謂的社會運動喔
Appeal to everyone in the so-called society to pay attention to
呼籲所謂社會的人大家都能夠重視
Moreover, legislation is required to promote the promotion of this hard hat
而且要立法才能夠把這一個安全帽的推動
able to move smoothly
能夠推動得很順利
After Director Zhuo promoted the legislation of such hard hats?
在卓處長推動了這樣的安全帽的立法之後呢
In fact, the accident
實際上這個事故傷害
Injuries have dropped from the third to the sixth cause of death
傷害已經從第三位死因降到第六位死因
3,000 fewer deaths per year
每年減少3000個人的死亡
This contributes greatly to the health of our people
這對我們全民的健康有很大的貢獻
that in the field of traumatic brain injury research
那在這個腦外傷的研究的領域當中
Our academic journal
我們這個在學術上的花表的期刊
It also ranks third in the world
也佔全球的第三位
So it's quite an achievement
所以這是相當傑出的這個成果
Of course you can imagine
當然大家可以想像得到
Director Qiu must have won many, many awards
這個邱署長一定得了很多很多的大獎
It's very long if we practice it all
如果我們把它練完的話就很長了
I only read a few
我只念幾個
Including the Individual Special Contribution Award of the 17th Medical Dedication Award
包括第十七屆醫療奉獻獎的個人特殊貢獻獎
Hua Mingning's Medical Contribution Award
華明寧的醫療貢獻獎
There is also the Legacy of the University of Pittsburgh in the United States
還有美國批子堡大學的這個Legacy
Lolriot Winners
Lolriot得獎人
and this Contribution Research Award from the Asia Pacific Alliance for Public Health
以及亞太公共衛生聯盟的這個貢獻研究獎
more than ten awards
十多個獎項
So we can invite Director Qiu today
所以我們今天能夠請到邱署長
come give us a speech
來幫我們演講
It's an honor for all of us
實在是我們大家的榮幸
then we
那我們
welcome with warm applause
以熱烈掌聲來歡迎
Director Qiu came to give us a speech today
邱署長來今天給我們做演講
Thanks
謝謝
Thank you Vice President Chen
謝謝陳副院長的
introduce
介紹
Then thank you for the opportunity to come here to share with you this time.
那麼也謝謝這一次有機會來這邊跟大家分享
So
那麼
I think this 25 years in fact I
我想這個25年事實上我
graduate
畢業
up to now
到現在已經
37, 38 years
37、38年了
So what have you been doing for the past ten years?
那這前面這十幾年在做什麼
I'll probably tell you
我大概跟大家講一下
Then the past ten years have been in
那麼前面這十幾年都是在
Managing patients with traumatic brain injuries
處理腦外傷的病人
or a brain tumor or something these patients
或者是腦瘤啦或什麼這些病人
Most of them are doing surgery. What?
大部分都在開刀啊什麼
So
那麼
I haven't
在我還沒有
When I entered prevention, I mostly did clinical work.
就是走入預防的時候呢我大部分都做臨床工作
clinical work is like this
臨床工作就是這樣
then for example
那麼譬如說
Let's talk about car accidents
我們車禍來講
then in
那麼在
Usually we used to be very early
通常我們過去在很早的時候
in the 1980s
1980年代的時候
The students were involved in car accidents at about five o'clock in the afternoon
學生出車禍都是在差不多下午五點
Five point trauma or six point trauma
五點創傷了或六點創傷
then sent to a small hospital
然後送到小醫院
Small hospital is sending
小醫院在送到
It's dangerous to see this
看了這個很危險
send it to the big hospital
再送到大醫院
The big hospital got there around seven or eight o'clock
大醫院到了那裡差不多七八點
Then start the treatment or start the examination
然後再開始治療或者是開始檢查
check check fiddle
檢查檢查弄弄弄
after finishing
弄完了以後
just start again
就又要開始
Tell the patient again
又要告訴病人說
to be operated on
要開刀
Then watch the patient operate
那看病人開刀
Because many patients have no family members
因為很多病人都是沒有家人的
often without family
常常沒有家人
and very young
而且都很年輕
At that time, most of them were people in their twenties.
那個時候大部分都是差不多二十歲上下的人
no family
沒有家人
Otherwise, when family members come
要不然有家人來的時候
almost eleven o'clock
差不多十點十一點
so we start the operation
所以我們開始開刀
almost twelve o'clock
差不多十二點
after eleven o'clock
十一點多
Every day is almost five days a week
每天都差不多一個禮拜有五天
open till dawn
開到天亮
often open till dawn
常常開到天亮
Then I often sleep in the car
那我常常在車子裡面睡覺
fall down
跌倒起來
Then go to the clinic again
然後又去看門診
life like this
就是這樣過日子
then
那時候就
I always think so
就常常這樣想
one day i sat there
有一天我就坐在那
when waking up in the car
在車子裡面睡醒的時候
Hey, this is too much
欸 這太多了吧 這個
too many accidents
車禍太多了
Do you want to find a way to go
是不是要想個辦法去
Do you want to come
要不要到
do something
做點什麼
take precautions
預防一下
just thought of saying
就想到說
Hey, very few people wear hard hats
欸 很少人戴安全帽
At that time, less than 5% of people wore hard hats
那時候不到5%的人戴安全帽
I just want to say that I should make a hard hat.
就想說應該去做安全帽
So this is the previous story
所以這個是前面的故事
It's all about cutting
就是都是在開刀
that's there
那在
before the lecture
在講課以前呢
I'll talk to you guys first because I'm watching today
我先跟各位 因為我看今天
I thought it was all like
我本來以為都是像
There are many scholars like Professor Chen
陳教授這樣學者很多
So I use English today
所以我今天是用英文的
present but
present 但是
There are a lot of pictures, it doesn't matter
圖片很多啦 沒關係
I speak Chinese
我都用中文講
then let me tell you first
那我先跟各位講
what does a brain injury look like
腦受傷是什麼樣
why is it called tofu
為什麼叫豆腐
Brain is almost the same as tofu
腦跟豆腐幾乎是一樣的
Its hardness is not much different
它的硬度是差不了太多
It's just that it has an extra layer of membrane package
只是它多了一層膜包組
arachnoid pack
叫做蜘蛛網膜包組
So it's fixed form
所以它固定形態
And then it has a lot of blood vessels
然後呢 它有很多血管
blood vessels many blood vessels
血管 血管很多
probably so
大概就這樣
Its hardness is about the same
它的硬度是差不多的
It's similar to tofu, which is firmer tofu.
跟豆腐 比較硬的豆腐差不多的
So this brain hit the ground
所以這個腦摔到地上
it's broken cracked
它是碎掉了 裂掉了
But I can't sew, I can't sew
但是又縫不起來 沒辦法縫
So it's broken it's broken
所以壞了就壞了
it a lot of people after brain injury
它很多人腦受傷以後
it got recovery just what
它得的恢復只是什麼
Just a reward function
只是代賞功能
Is to use other areas to reward
就是用其他區域來代賞
So the brain is broken and never recovers.
所以腦是壞了就沒有再恢復了
what about this brain
那麼這個腦呢
What happens when we get hurt
我們受傷以後會產生怎麼樣
The first one will produce
第一個會產生
Our mildest is called a concussion
我們最輕微的叫做腦震盪
Everyone, maybe most people think that
各位也許一般人都覺得說
Wow, a serious concussion
哇 腦震盪很嚴重
Concussion, actually concussion is
腦震盪 其實腦震盪就是
One day his bones are like this
一天他小骨這樣
But just faint
但是昏去就是了
you don't hold up anymore
你不要再撐起來
But the brain
但是腦部啊
No structural damage seen
看不到什麼結構性的傷害
Structural damage cannot be seen
結構性的傷害看不到
This is called a concussion
這個叫做腦震盪
in our general
在我們一般來講
He was unconscious for less than five minutes.
他都昏迷都在五分鐘以內
very slight
很輕微
Well, if you have a brain contusion, it's more serious.
那麼如果腦挫傷就比較嚴重了
brain contusion is what can see
腦挫傷就是可以看到什麼
I owe even
偶欠偶欠
bruising phenomenon
瘀青的現象
it's called a brain contusion
這叫腦挫傷
constitutional brain
contitutional brain
brain contusion
腦挫傷就
The coma will last longer
昏迷時間會比較長
That's an injury
那這個都是一個受傷
But the worst thing is
但是最嚴重的還是
really bad brain trauma
真正的很厲害的腦的創傷
episodic hemorrhage
接著引發敘發性的出血
This is all scary
這個都是才可怕
What about after this episodic hemorrhage?
那麼這個敘發性的出血以後呢
often have this phenomenon
常常有這種現象
that is
就是說
Brain injury right after the car accident
車禍剛剛發生的時候腦受傷
After a while
分過一下子
maybe a concussion
也許是個腦震盪
But one of them
但是呢其中一條
Broken blood vessel
血管破了
he bleeds slowly
他就慢慢出血
Patient, you see that kid was fine when he came home.
病人你看那個小孩回家的時候還很好
when i got home i said
回到家裡的時候我說
I had a fight with my classmates
我跟同學打個架
Or create something for the car
或者是給車子創了一下
After returning home
回到家裡以後啊
He said he had a headache
他就說他頭有點痛
want to go to sleep
想要去休息睡覺一下
Well, mom, if you pay attention, it's fine.
那麼媽媽呢如果很注意的話就好
If you don't pay attention, you will see
沒有注意的話呢就看到
The child suddenly started humming loudly at night
小孩突然晚上就開始大哼了
weird kids snoring
奇怪小孩都會打哼
because he can't breathe
因為他呼吸不好
respiratory tract is not very good
呼吸道不是很好
just unconscious
就昏迷不醒
Then there are children
那麼也有小孩呢
Sent to the hospital for surgery to save him
送到醫院去開刀可以救回來
but
但是呢
Many of them may not be saved
很多都是不一定救得回來
if you're not careful at night
如果你晚上沒有很小心的話
so he often
所以他常常會
Sometimes there will be a delay in happening
會有時候會延遲一段時間在發生
He woke up with a concussion first
他先一個腦震盪醒過來
But what about when we go back?
但是呢回去以後呢
Bleeding again or getting bad again
又出血或者是又變壞了
or how
或怎麼樣
So this brain injury is complicated
所以這個腦受傷是很複雜的
then we almost
那我們幾乎
I also hand it over to you today
我今天也交給各位呢
five tips
五個訣竅
Even a brain injury is important
就是腦受傷也有很重要的
Tips everyone should know
一般人要知道的訣竅
that is
就是說
what about the first one
第一個呢
Brain injury, you must pay attention to it
腦受傷呢你一定要注意它
do you have a headache
有沒有頭痛
getting stronger
越來越厲害
or especially getting stronger
或特別是越來越厲害
The second one started vomiting
第二個開始偶吐
We usually have more than two
我們平常兩次以上
Occasional vomiting is common in children
就小孩子偶吐是很平常的
But what if more and more
但是呢如果越來越多
or more than twice
或者是超過兩次以上
take it slow and be careful
就慢慢就要小心
what about the third one
那麼第三個呢
See if the consciousness has deteriorated
看看意識有沒有變壞
It's just that people don't know clearly
就是人清不清楚
so sometimes
所以有時候呢
Wake him up often
要常常給他叫醒啊這些
So the fourth one is
那麼所以第四個呢就是
often have to wake him up
常常要叫醒他
every first night
就是每個第一天晚上
maybe every hour to wake him up
也許每個鐘頭就要去叫醒他
wake him up
叫醒他
or the next day
要不然到第二天
maybe gone
也許就沒了
It's gone, it's always like this
就沒了 常常這樣
What about the last one?
那最後一個呢 就說
if anything
如果有什麼
what's changed in particular
特別有什麼變化 不管什麼
Which aspect has changed?
哪一方面的變化 電閒啊
or how he will happen
或怎麼樣 他也會發生
many complications
很多的病發症
then be careful
那麼就要很小心的
It's better to go to the doctor quickly
趕快還是送醫比較好
So generally speaking
那麼所以一般來說呢
he has a lot of symptoms
他的症狀非常多
Wait a minute and I'll mention a lot of symptoms
等一下我都會提到很多的症狀
But observation is the most important thing
但是觀察是最要緊的
Especially the changes in his process
尤其他的過程的變化這些
So in a brain injured person
那麼在對一個腦受傷的人
is very important
是非常重要
So this brain injury is important
那麼話說這個腦受傷很重要
intermediate prevention of these
中間的預防這些
Well, there's actually one more
那麼其實還有一個
More importantly, the sequelae
更重要的是後遺症
Except you have to save him in the acute stage
除了你急性期要救他
What about the sequelae? It's terrible.
這個後遺症呢 很可怕
What about the aftermath?
那麼後遺症呢
What if ordinary people
如果一般的人呢
he produces a slight
他產生輕微的
Severe trauma, he must have sequelae
重的創傷 他一定有後遺症
his finger
他的手指
he must have sequelae
他一定有後遺症
His hands and feet are bad
他的手腳不好啦
or generate
或者是產生
Lungs or something
肺啦 或怎麼樣都有
But what about a mild concussion?
但是輕微的腦震盪呢
Recently, more and more sequelae have been found
最近發現越來越多有後遺症
then probably
那麼大概
you pay attention
你注意看
If we roughly collected literature from all over the world
如果我們大概收集了全世界的文獻
Probably at least 30 kinds
大概至少有30種
30 kinds
30種
Bad from long term memory
從長期的記憶變不好
headache dizziness various
頭痛 頭暈 各種
probably collected
大概收集起來
can't concentrate
注意力沒辦法集中
tinnitus insomnia blah blah blah
耳鳴 失眠等等等等等等
There are about 30 kinds in total
大概總共有30種
So what about the aftermath?
所以這個後遺症呢
In fact, it has a lot to do with your rest the last two weeks.
事實上跟你前兩週的休息也很有關係
So generally we tell patients
所以一般我們都會告訴病人
It's just about the first two weeks to rest.
就是大概前兩週要休息啦這些
Then this is a comparison
那麼這個是一個比較
At the same time, some others also found
同時也另外有些人也發現
That is, even if the patient fully recovered
就是說即使這個病人完全恢復了
he can't see what the symptoms are like
他看不出有什麼症狀有什麼樣
but if you
但是如果你
while giving him a test called neurobehavioral
給他做一個叫做神經行為的測試的時候
Neurobehavioral tests are now more and more developed
現在神經行為的測試越來越發達
then you will find out
那你就會發現呢
What about him
他呢
This is about 30% of people
這個大概有30%的人
sometimes weird
有時候會怪怪的
What about this weird one?
那這個怪怪的呢
Only his dearest mother
只有他的最親的媽媽
or his wife
或者他的妻子
or a spouse
或者是配偶
or what
或者什麼樣
he knows he's changing
他知道他有在變化
so this
所以這個
Brain injuries are really complicated
腦受傷真的是非常複雜
That's because he's like tofu
那因為他就像豆腐一樣
So there is no way to recover this tofu
所以這個豆腐是沒有辦法恢復的
Therefore, it is still necessary to do the function of prevention
所以還是要做到預防的功用
Then I'll probably put this more basic try first
那我大概先把這個比較基本的嘗試
let me tell you first
先跟大家講一下
And then we start looking at this
然後我們就開始看一下這個
why do we do these things
為什麼我們要做這些事
then see the next one
那麼請看下一張
So maybe I'll introduce
那麼大概我會介紹一下說
What is the significance of setting up this center over there?
我們在那邊成立這個中心的意義在哪裡
Then we will tell you what is called transformation research.
然後我們會跟各位講一下什麼叫轉異研究
Finally we look at our recent research
最後我們看看最近的我們的研究
future direction
未來的方向
I will talk about transformation research for about 25 minutes
轉異研究這個就我差不多講差不多25分鐘
I will talk about the current research below for about 30 minutes
底下的現在的研究我講差不多30分鐘
Then the previous research is life-saving for us.
那麼前面的研究我們都是救命的
Later, I found out that the sequelae caused by it were too many problems.
後來發現說它造成的後遺症很問題太多了
So the latter is saving something
所以後面這個都是在救什麼
functional improvements
功能上的改善
Just remembering this and see if it helps
就是記憶這些看看能不能有幫忙
how do i do this
我怎麼這些
So probably my focus today is to mention the next one
所以大概我今天重點就是提一下下一張
So why do this research
那麼為什麼要做這個研究
This has just been possible because it is very serious
這個剛才已經可能因為它是非常嚴重
because it is tofu
因為是豆腐
tofu victim
豆腐受害
After the injury, he has a very serious mortality rate
受傷以後呢,他有很嚴重的死亡率
There are a lot of things like morbidity rate and comorbidities
跟致病率,病發症這些很多
So it has a very big impact on society and the economy
所以他對社會,對經濟的衝擊非常大
What about the whole world, what about a year
那麼全世界呢,一年呢
Approximately 9 million people experience traumatic brain injury
大概有九百萬人發生腦創傷
As for Taiwan, about 100,000 a year
那麼台灣呢,一年大概有十萬
The 100,000 is just to go to the hospital to seek medical treatment
這個十萬只是說去醫院找求醫的
There are only 100,000 people, and there are probably even more people who did not go to the hospital
就十萬人,沒有去醫院的恐怕更多
Then this may be more than three times
那麼這個可能大概有三倍以上
So why in America recently
那麼為什麼在美國最近呢
attach great importance to this thing
非常的重視這個東西
Because of the wars in Iraq and Afghanistan
因為伊拉克跟阿富汗戰爭
What about many American soldiers?
很多美國的軍人呢
did not die on the battlefield
在戰場上沒有死掉
But after he returned to his hometown, he began to have a lot of sequelae
但是他回到本土以後就開始產生很多的後遺症
memory starts to decline
記憶力開始衰退
then start to have a headache
那麼開始常常頭痛
dizziness poor balance
頭暈 平衡不好
Insomnia occurs many times
失眠 很多很多都出現
In fact, some people don't feel that there is any serious injury at all.
其實有些人根本就感覺上沒有什麼很重的傷害
But it's the same when he comes back
可是他回來也是這樣
So these problems have caused the whole world to study this so-called
所以這些問題就造成全世界都在研究這個叫做
Brain Trauma Research
腦創傷的研究
In particular, the WHO also has more and more disasters
特別WHO也因為災難越來越多
Therefore, special emphasis is placed on the importance of brain trauma.
所以也是特別的強調這個對腦創傷的重視
next
下一張
this is 1987
這是1987年
then we will
那時候我們就
Did a simple research and found out that
做了一個簡單的研究就發現說
Taiwan is probably
台灣大概是
It's probably the area with the worst traumatic brain injury.
大概是這個腦外傷最嚴重的區域
we found this
我們發現了這個
The most serious patient he than
最嚴重的病人他比
about twice as much outside
外面多一倍左右
so moderate
那麼中等度的
Of course we use
這個當然我們是用
Grasco Comasca
Grasco Comasca
This is a two table to measure
這一個兩表來測
3 to 8 points are called severe
3到8分的叫做嚴重
9 to 12 points are called
9到12分的叫做
Moderate
中等度
12 to 15 points are called mild
12分到15分的叫做輕度
We found that mild
我們就發現輕度
rarely less
很少比較少
The whole is more serious
整個都比較嚴重
next
下一張
so
所以
It was the locomotive at that time
當時就是當時機車呢
In 1987, there were only 7 million locomotives
1987年機車只有700萬輛
Now it has reached 14 million
現在已經到1400萬輛
So
那麼
All the vehicles inside this one
這個其中所有的車輛裡面
all vehicles approximately
所有車輛大概
If there were about 10 million vehicles at that time
如果當時的車輛大概1000萬輛
Of the 10 million vehicles, 7 million are locomotives
1000萬輛裡面700萬輛是機車
so serious
所以很嚴重
And what?
而且呢
Few people wear hard hats
肌膚很少人戴安全帽
so so
那麼所以
Top 10 causes of death at the time
當時死亡的十大死因
are hurt
都是傷
accident injury
意外事故傷害
So this is very serious in Taiwan
所以這個是台灣非常嚴重的
But at that time everyone was used to it
那但是那個時候大家也習以為常
public security
公安
A lot of people are like, if we talk about prevention or something
很多人就跟 如果我們講到預防或怎麼樣
They'll all tell you, ah, there's no way this accident could have been prevented.
他們都會告訴你說 啊這意外不可能會預防
But in fact, prevention is the most effective
但事實上這個是預防是最有效果的
So at that time, I couldn't find any information.
所以當時呢 也找不到什麼資料
Because health insurance hasn't started yet, health insurance has just started
因為健保也還沒開始 健保剛剛開始了
Well, so, there were very few preventive strategies at the time.
那麼 所以 預防的策略當時幾乎很少
So this is Taiwan, why was it serious at that time?
所以這個是台灣為什麼那時候很嚴重就是這樣
Next I think this is the center of our establishment
下一張 那我想這個是我們成立的中心
Divided into four groups, I won’t talk about this one. The next one
分成四個組 這個我就不談了 下一張
What about so-called translational studies?
那麼所謂的轉譯研究呢
Just want scientists, doctors
就是要科學家 醫師
and many of our research institutes
還有我們很多跟很多的研究機構
Like the National Institutes of Health and cooperation with NIDA in the United States
像國家衛生院 還有跟美國的NIDA合作
INIH in the United States is the cooperation of the National Institutes of Health
美國INIH就是美國國家衛生院合作
Then our whole study
那我們這個整個研究
Much of this process is carried out together with these institutions.
這個過程很多都是跟這幾個機構一起來進行
next
下一張
Then of course you need a lot of equipment
那麼當然要需要很多的設備
including genes
包括基因的
include this
包括這個
spectrometer these
支譜儀這些
tissue bank
組織庫
What's more special is the functional MRI
那比較特別的是功能性的MRI
Then we just bought one too
那我們剛好也買了一部
the best
最好的
the latest in the world
世界上現在最新的
So our function for this memory
所以我們對於這個記憶的功能
also did a lot
也做了非常的多
Then again it is very important for this
那再來就是很重要的就是對於這個
IRB
IRB
that is
就是說
research ethics
研究倫理的
This and this clinical trial center
這個還有這個臨床試驗的中心
this is very important
這個都是非常重要的
one
一個
Core Facility is our main research
Core Facility就是我們主要的研究的
center
中心
next
下一張
Then we are at Taipei Medical University
那我們在台北醫學大學
in fact
事實上
At that time, many of the schools were doing clinical trials.
這個學校當時很多都是做臨床試驗
especially in nerve
特別是在神經
Medicine, then we have three hospitals running at the same time
醫學 那我們有三個醫院同時在進行
of course for this
那當然對這個
Ethical review is very strict
倫理的審核非常的嚴格
Then also through WHO's FIRCAP
那麼也通過WHO的FIRCAP
These next ones, in fact, we
這些 下一張 那事實上我們跟
The other six hospitals in the province have a total of more than 8,700 beds
全省其他六個醫院 總共8700多床
have a common doing this
有共同在做這個
Collaborative Research Understanding
合作的研究的了解
next
下一張
then this is where we are
那麼這個是我們在
This is a famous Elsep
這個是一個很有名的Elsep
them
他們
Made one called Cyber ​​Sport
做的一個叫做Cyber Sport
Cyber Sport Light
Cyber Sport Light
That said, the world's research on traumatic brain injury
那就是說 全世界對腦外傷的研究
it ranks in the end
它的排名 到底
its publication and its influence
它的出版 它的影響力怎麼樣
What about our first time in 2007?
那我們在2007年呢 就第一次呢
enter the seventh place
進到第七名
That person's research is into the fourth place next
那個人的研究是進到第四名 下一張
By 2009, we had entered the third place
到了2009年呢 我們已經進到第三名
Personally still in third place
到個人還是在第三名
next
下一張
So what about 2011?
那麼到了2011年呢
What about the word brain trauma?
用這個腦創傷這個字眼來做呢
we've already run to the first place
我們已經跑到第一位了
then in this
那麼在這個
Personally still third
個人方面還是第三位
So the whole research aspect
所以整個研究方面呢
Our range is pretty wide
我們的範圍蠻廣的
wait a minute everyone can see
等一下各位可以各位看
We are working on the four levels of depression
我們從四個轉抑的層面都在進行
next
下一張
sorry
對不起
this
這個
The voice is hoarse
聲音講一講就是沙啞
wait a minute i tell you why
等一下我告訴你們為什麼
So what is repression medicine?
那什麼叫轉抑醫學
Depression medicine was first proposed
轉抑醫學最早被提出來
This is all copied from the US National Institutes of Health
這都是從美國國家衛生院裡面copy出來
Depression medicine is of course from
那轉抑醫學當然是從
Enter this from Basic Medicine
從基礎醫學進入這個
Use basic medicine to the last
把基礎醫學的東西最後用到
Applying it to humans is depression-reversal medicine
用到人身上就是轉抑醫學
next
下一張
Then repression research is repression
那麼轉抑研究呢就是轉抑
Use this underline basis for translational medicine
用這個 underline basis for translational medicine
it's mostly transfer research
它主要是轉移研究
That is to say, from a team of scientists
就是說從科學家一個團隊
scientist link到 basic science
scientist link到 basic science
clinical research
跟臨床的研究
Then take the result of this base
然後把這個基礎的結果
clinical career
用到經過臨床事業
It is used in clinical daily treatment
用到臨床的這個平日的治療上面
This is called transferring some
這個叫做轉移一些
that is
就是說
For example, experts from animal
譬如說專家從動物
Slowly research out a lot of things
慢慢地研究出很多東西
reapply this thing to people
把這個東西再用到人身上
This is called transfer
這個就叫轉移
next
下一張
So a story in the US Capitol
所以在美國國會一個故事
I also tell you
我也講給各位聽
It's America's national restroom.
就是美國的國家衛生間
Do a lot of basic research
做了好多好多的基礎研究
That basic research has been increasing
那個基礎研究一直在增加
Then Congress couldn't take it anymore
後來國會就受不了了
that is
就是說
We don't want to know why
We don't want to know why
because why has done too much
因為為什麼已經做太多了
but they need to know
但是他們要知道說
When can be applied to people
When 何時可以用到人身上
That is to say, you do so much
就是說這個你做那麼多
dogs, cats, what
狗啊貓啊什麼這些
Then we don't think it's important
那這個我們覺得都不重要
When can these successful treatments
什麼時候可以把這些這種成功的治療
use it on people
用到人身上
So at that time
所以那個時候呢
Head of NIH
NIH 的頭頭
It's called Alius Gehoni
就是叫做Alius Gehoni
He invented a tool called Translational
他就發明了一個叫做Translational
Clinical Science comes out in New England Magazine
Clinical Science 在新英格蘭雜誌裡面出來
He used from Bench to Best Sight
他是用從Bench 到Best Sight
Bench is basic research to Best Sight to Practice
Bench 就是基礎研究到Best Sight 到Practice
What about this idea?
那這種觀念呢
has been accepted by people all over the world
已經被全世界的大家所接受
so
所以
It will gradually develop into the stage of T1 and T2
就慢慢發展成T1跟T2這個階段
Then in 2010 the next one
那麼到了2010年下一張
And developed into T1 to T4
又發展成T1到T4
Then this has a greater impact on human beings
那這個對人類影響更大
Not necessarily from cats and dogs
並不一定是從貓狗動物來的
Even from clinical research
甚至呢 從臨床的研究呢
be able to run to the benefit of all mankind
能夠跑到對全人類有幫忙
impact in the population
impact in the population
It's the whole population that helps
就是整個人口有幫忙
This is a transfer
這個也算轉移
So the first transfer stage
所以第一個轉移階段
From basic to clinical application
就從基礎到臨床的應用
What about the second clinic?
第二個臨床呢
turn it into something
就要把它變成什麼
called guidance
叫做指引
It is because of a lot of accumulated clinical experience
就是因為臨床的累積經驗很多
turn it into a guide
把它變成指引
guideline means
指引就是說
Everyone can follow this line
所有的人都可以依照這個該line
do something
去做一些事情
For example, the treatment of the external cavity of the head
比如說頭部外腔的治療
We accumulate from experience
我們從經驗累積
From all aspects of research
從研究各方面
make it a line
把它做成一個該line
The line is then used on people
該line然後用到人身上
Apply it to all patients like this, everyone’s treatment methods will be compared
用到所有的病人身上 這樣子呢 大家的治療方式呢 就會比較
The quality is relatively high and the standard is relatively high
品質就比較高 水準也比較高
Then you can use Gynein and Health Practice
然後呢 你可以從Gynein還可以用到Health Practice
Go to this and then apply to other, even another country or something
到這個 再去應用到其他的 甚至另外一個國家或怎麼樣
This is Health Practice is Gynein
這個都是Health Practice 就是Gynein
So he divides this into T1 T2 T3
所以他把這個分成T1 T2 T3
Then Health Practice is based on these applications, and finally it is used on the population
然後Health Practice 就是從這些應用呢 最後呢 用到人口上面
So today I will talk to you from these four directions.
那我今天呢 就從這四個方向 跟各位講
then the next one
那麼 下一張
What about the first one? Let me give you an example from basic medicine to clinical application.
那第一個呢 我舉一個例子給各位 從基礎醫學到臨床應用
Well, everyone knows that there is a drug called Propofol
那麼大家知道 這個 有一個Propofol 這個藥呢
it will it is an antioxidant Antioxidant
它會 它是一個抗氧化的Antioxidant
then it can also
那麼它也可以
have this neuroprotective function
有這個神經保護的功能
This is already proof on the basis
這個在基礎已經proof
So what if we apply it to people?
那麼如果我們把它用在人身上呢
In fact, this anesthesiology department has always been useful.
那其實這個麻醉科也一直常常有用
So some patients work and some patients don't
所以有些病人有用有些病人沒有用
next
下一張
Then find out that this is useful
那就發現說這種有用的呢
There is osracial of 2.8
就有2.8的osracial
It's what helped this result
就是它的對這個結果有幫忙的
probably so
大概是這樣
We have also published this in the literature
這個我們也都發表在文獻上
next
下一張
Then in this process
那麼這個過程裡面
We did about 7
我們大概做了7個
4 of them compare with results
其中有4個比較有結果
Then I'll be Gynein soon
那麼我就很快的Gynein
Of course you don't need to talk
當然不用講
More fruitful is to say
比較有結果的就是說
we find on animals
我們在動物上發現
If you treat a patient with a brain sore
如果你治療一個腦瘡傷的病人
If you use a monitor
如果你用一個monitor
A catheter can measure the pressure in his brain
導管可以測量他的腦壓
Constantly measure brain pressure
不斷的測量腦壓
That is, the result of treatment will be much better
就是治療的結果會好很多
If the pressure is high we put some water out
如果壓力很高的時候我們就放一些水出來
if or with some medicine
如果或者用一些藥
This is better for patient outcomes
這樣子對病人結果更好
Then this proves that he has 4.3 times the effect
那這個證明他有4.3倍的效果
Is hyperbaric oxygen effective?
那另外高壓氧是不是有效
high pressure
高壓氧
Hyperbaric Oxygen Chambers
Hyperbolic Oxygen Chambles
So this proves that he works for subpolar patients
那麼這個證明他對亞極性的病人有效
But it doesn't help a lot with polarity
但是對極性的並沒有很多的幫忙
Then from this
那另外從這個
Another special
另外一個比較特別的就是
In treatment we use a
在治療上我們用一個
partial pressure, oxygen partial pressure directly into the brain
分壓、氧分壓直接放到腦部
Well, recently the whole world has also begun to be popular
那麼最近全世界也都在開始在流行
What did it turn out to be?
那結果發現呢
What if you measure the partial pressure directly?
如果你直接測量分壓呢
he will turn out well
他的結果會很好
Then I think these details I will no longer
那我想這些細節我就不再
What about this one, especially for people with lung problems?
那麼這個呢特別對肺有問題的人
If you have lung problems
如果你肺有問題的人
you want to put it
你要想把它
Oxygen pressure and oxygen height are more difficult
氧壓、氧身高比較困難
So however you can get from the machine
所以但是你可以從機器
Turn it up with a FIO2
用一個FIO2把它調高
This is especially useful for patients, and it is very helpful for patients with trauma
這對病人特別有費,同時有創傷的病人,很有幫忙
So these are all evidence of T1, which means we have done
所以這些都是T1的一個證據,就是說我們做過的
Then if T2 is based on clinical experience, make it Gaili guidelines
那麼如果從T2是從臨床的經驗,把它做成Gaili指引
Then we made a Taiwan Gaili around 2007
那我們大概在2007年就做了一個Taiwan Gaili
This is all published in the literature
這個都在文獻上都發表
Then we will establish an Asian Gaili with Japan, South Korea, and China
那麼之後我們就跟日本、韓國、還有中國成立一個Asian Gaili
This is also in Gaili Nero, which is the magazine with the highest score in our neurotrauma
這個也在Gaili Nero,這個是我們神經創傷裡面最分數最高的一個雜誌
Then this, the next one I'll see...
那麼這個,下一張我看就...
Then this has been published in this, published in bilingual
那這個已經發表在這個,用雙語來發表
Then whatever the book is published
那麼不管是書都出版了
And besides, he's also...
那麼另外呢,他也在...
Published in international literature
在國際的文獻上發表
what about this one i wait
那麼這一個呢我等一下
Now all our neurosurgeries use this
這個現在我們所有神經外科呢都是用著這個
doing treatment
在做治療
everyone has one
大家都有一個
something like a biboy
好像biboy一樣的東西
Of course it's still being updated
當然現在還在改版
maybe wait a minute i brought the basics
也許等一下我帶了基本來
then the first few
那麼前幾個
I can send you any questions
發問的我就可以送給大家
next
下一張
Then we use the British Sign Level of Evidence
那麼我們是用英國的Sign Level of Evidence
to define him
來做界定他的
evidence
證據
next
下一張
Then
然後
Our recommendation also uses Sign Grade
我們的recommendation呢也是用Sign Grade
next
下一張
Then it includes these eight items
那這裡面呢包括這個八項
emergency room treatment
就是急診室治療
Determination of brain pressure
腦壓的測定
how to do it
怎麼樣來做到底
cerebral perfusion pressure
腦的灌流壓
With this Fruits Therapy
跟這個Fruits Therapy
Then Sedative Nutrition these
那麼Sedative Nutrition這些
i will watch your brain
我會看你的腦部
I can
我會
the second one
第二張
People's treatment of these next
人次的治療這些 下一張
Then this is one of the consensus in Asia
那這個是亞洲的共識的一個
meeting next
會議 下一張
then we are probably here
那我們大概在這個
this meeting this is not a
這個會議 這個不是一個
evidence base it is a consensus
evidence base 它是一個 consensus
Then we have some consensus on these four themes
那我們在這四個主題呢 有一些共識
next
下一張
So, for example, what do you think, this brain pressure
那麼譬如說 大家認為呢 這個腦壓
is a therapeutic concept, not just a tool
是一個治療的觀念 不單是一個工具
Of course this has
那當然這個有
My ventricle from the foreign ventricle is the most effective treatment
我從外來的腦室的陰流 是最有效的治療
What about brain infusion pressure?
那麼對於腦灌輸壓呢
He thinks no less than 60
他認為不要低於60
At the same time, this should not exceed 70
同時呢 這個不要大於70
This is an important concept
這個都是很重要的一個觀念
next
下一張
What about the other one? I think it is
那另外 這個呢 認為是
This is called decompression
這個叫做開爐解壓
Open up the bones of the brain
把腦的骨頭整個打開
When the brain is swollen, the pressure can be squeezed out
讓腦腫的時候壓力可以擠出來的
We think this is also good
這個我們認為也是不錯的
especially in very malignant brain tumors
特別是在很惡性的腦腫
Here I'm going to talk about a brain
這裡呢我就要講一個腦部
there are a lot of different
有一些很多不一樣的
This tofu nao is different from tofu
這個豆腐腦跟豆腐不一樣的
The tofu shattered on the ground
豆腐摔到地上就碎了
But the brain has many blood vessels
但是腦呢因為很多血管
It has an omentum wrapped
它有一個網膜包著
After being injured, it will take a while
受傷以後呢它到一段時間會
horribly swollen
腫得非常可怕
sometimes when you cut
有時候你開刀的時候
when you turn it on
你把它打開的時候
That brain looks like this, what does it look like?
那個腦像這個像這個什麼
We're called Dry Bread
我們叫做Dry Bread
It's like dry bread suddenly absorbs water
就是乾麵包突然吸到水一樣
swell up so fast swell up very fast
腫起來好快腫得非常快
This is the same place in the brain
這個是腦部一樣的地方
because its blood flow is affected
因為它血流受到影響
Its venous return is not working
它的靜脈回流不行的
swell so fast
腫得好快
So this sometimes this has to do a decompression
所以這個有時候這個必須做一個解壓
Then the other sedatives are also considered to be
那另外鎮定劑大家也認為是
Anti-oxidation is helpful for this generation defect rate
對這個代缺率抗氧化有幫忙
next
下一張
then in the United States
那麼在美國
In 200 years, the United States made a survey
美國200年就做了一個概賴
When entering Taiwan
當時要進入台灣的時候
We put America's one guide to the next
我們把美國的一個指引下一張
just take it
就拿過來
They believe that hyperventilation, political and economic agents
他們認為呼吸過度、政經劑
These political and economic agents are still useful
這些政經劑還有用
None of these hyperventilations help
這些呼吸過度都沒有用
next
下一張
Let's see if it works locally
我們就到底它本土行不行
We have treated more than 580 patients in Taiwan
我們就在台灣做了580幾個病人
Proven brain pressure measurement on the first day
證明腦壓測定在第一天
with an average of one to three days
跟平均的一到三天的平均
all meaningful
都是有意義的
next
下一張
At the same time, it is meaningless for perfusion pressure
同時在對於灌流壓是沒有什麼意義的
Measuring means nothing
測量沒有什麼意義
It is also meaningless for breathing hyperventilation
對呼吸hyperventilation也是沒有意義的
next
下一張
So the whole T3
所以整個T3來講
From empirical evidence to Health practice
從實證到Health practice
We have about three larger ones
我們大概有三個比較大的
The first is that we put the American
第一個是我們把美國的
It should be used in Taiwan
該來用到台灣來
think there is
覺得還有
Then we did the case ourselves
然後我們就自己做了該案
After you did the case yourself?
自己做了該案以後呢
now at present
現在目前呢
Promoted by Taiwan Society of Neurosurgery
是台灣神經外科學會在推動
then in addition
那麼另外
Our case in Asia
我們在亞洲的該案
also did part
也做了一部分
Then this year will continue
那麼今年還會繼續
Then come out one by one
那麼一個一個題目出來
then we'll use it to
那麼我們會把它用到
Asia
亞洲地區
We have the same treatment model
我們有同樣的治療模式
especially for asians
特別是對亞洲人
everyone has
大家有
international consensus
國際上的共識
Then the treatment of patients will be better
然後對病人的治療會更好
This is what Action should come
這個是Action該來
next
下一張
then there are many more
那麼另外還有很多
for example
譬如說
we still have to do
我們還有做
this
這個
parenteral nutrition
靜脈營養的
in 48 hours
在48小時內呢
What about this patient?
對這個病人呢
very helpful
很有幫忙
next
下一張
then in addition
那麼另外
WHO has a table on quality of life
生活品質的WHO有一個表格
yes to this
對這個是
quality of life
對生活品質的
Measurements are helpful
測量是很有幫忙的
next
下一張
Um
嗯
then compare
那麼比較
interesting
有趣
Of course, this is a health insurance treatment file
當然這是健保治療檔
We also found in the health insurance treatment files that
健保治療檔裡面我們也發現說
The treatment file of this health insurance
這種健保的治療檔
We found patients with brain injuries
我們發現腦受傷的病人
suddenly this
突然這個
skezophrenia is higher
skezophrenia比較高
this may have some
這個也許有一些
citation problems
引用上的問題
or the coding on the login
或者是登錄上的coding
It was the problem of coding at that time
就是當時coding的問題
But this is just a reference
不過這個倒是做一個參考
The next one is the health insurance treatment file
下一張這是健保治療檔
This is also in our database
這個也是一個我們的資料庫裡面
The health insurance treatment file also found that
健保治療檔也發現說
after brain injury
腦受傷以後
its this
它的這個
generate this
產生這個
3 times higher rate of zeitgeist syndrome
時代症的比例高了3倍
will generate this in the future
將來產生這個
This has been confirmed in many studies
這個已經在很多的研究已經證實了
Especially the full phone
特別是那個全機手
Nearly 60 to 70% of the majority have developed geriatric syndrome
大部分將近有六七成都產生了老年時代症
It doesn't have to be old age, it's arctimer, Alzheimer's disease
不一定是老年,是arctimer,阿茲海默症
So all over the world, there is a correlation between traumatic brain injury and the age and Alzheimer's
所以這個在全世界,目前都在腦外傷跟時代跟阿茲海默相關聯性
Successive reports have been brought out
陸續的報告一直帶出來
The next one, more importantly, this is two studies
下一張,比較重要的就是,這個是兩個研究
For our future T3 to T4, one is the research of Professor Wang Longde
對於我們將來T3進入T4,一個是王龍德教授的研究
He proves that wearing a helmet is better than not wearing a helmet
他是證明這個帶安全帽,比沒有帶安全帽好
The result is 2.6 times better than what we did ourselves 2.1 times better
結果要好2.6倍,我們自己做的是2.1倍
It is similar to international research, the next one
跟國際上的研究是差不多的,下一張
So let's talk about this fourth one, we call it T4
所以我們就開始講這個第四個,我們叫T4
From this Health practice to Health in
從這個Health practice到Health in
impact in population
impact in population
Here we are from 25 years
在這裡我們就從25年來
have been building a lot of databases
就一直在建立很多的資料庫
These four databases are relatively large
這四個資料庫比較大的
just have this
就是有這個
There are more than 180,000 cases used in epidemiology
流行病學用的有18萬多例
The clinical database has more than 2000 cases
臨床的資料庫有2000多例
There are more than 1,400 cases of data registration of clinical water collection and provincial merchants
臨床的集水省商的資料登入有1400多例
And here is the org library
還有這是組織庫
About nearly 20,000 Samples
大概將近2萬個Sample
This is Huadong's situation
這是花東的情形
next
下一張
I don't need to talk about this
這個就不用再講
This is the org library
這是組織庫
This is what we discovered at the time
這個我們當時就發現說
There are differences between Taipei and Hualien
臺北跟花蓮有它不一樣的地方
The incidence rate in Hualien is about
花蓮它的發生率大概是
388 is twice that of Taipei
388就是臺北的兩倍
The death rate in Hualien is four times that of Taipei.
那麼花蓮的死亡率卻是高達台北的四倍
And he has a higher ratio of truck to cargo
而且他的車貨的比例更高
next
下一張
We also found that the counties and cities in the east and outlying islands
我們也發現到說東部的各縣市跟離島
Where the ratio of their locomotives is relatively high
他們機車比較高的比例地方
Their mortality rate and incidence rate are high
他們的死亡率跟發生率都高
next
下一張
Then we were also in 1993 and 1997
那麼後來我們也在93年跟97年
Almost all the hospitals in the country have done
幾乎把全國的醫院都做了
Then it can be concluded that this is dead 230
那麼得出來這個是死的230
About 230 people per 100,000 people
每10萬人口大概是230個人
About 70% are caused by vehicles
大概七成是車貨引起的
That's a very high proportion in the world
那這個都是世界上很高的一個比例
Then this was also published in the American Journal of Public Health
那這個在在美國公共衛生雜誌也發表過
next
下一張
so the whole process
所以整個過程呢
The most important thing for us is to promote the protection process
我們最重要的還是要推這個保護的過程
So I did a lot of research
所以做了非常多的研究
There is a way to push this
才有辦法推動這個
this
這個
Hard hat legislation
安全帽的立法
then the next one
那麼下一張
Of course, a lot of international comparisons have also been made.
那當然也做了很多國際比較
use it to cite the next
拿來引證下一張
Then this is the picture we often use
那這個是我們常常用的圖
Tell me all, let's see if you smile when you wear the hard hat this time
都給我講話 看你這次到安全帽有沒有笑
This time it's in Portuguese, and I don't understand it either.
這次是葡萄牙語 我也聽不懂
it's a case a case
是一個案子 一個案子
This is so funny I don't even have to talk
這個很有笑 我都不用講話
Everyone knows that the helmet is very funny
大家看了就知道安全帽很有笑
so we are in taipei
所以我們就在台北
At that time in Taipei, in Taipei in 1984
台北那時候 1984年在台北
Just push hard hats, not without legislation
就推動安全帽 不是沒有立法
At that time it was to fetch land
那時候就是去取地
Later, I found out that during these four months
後來就發現說在這四個月裡面
in four months
四個月裡面就是
More than 500 people were mobilized by Taipei City Traffic Continental
台北市交通大陸的動員500多個人
Crack down everywhere without wearing a hard hat
到處在取締 沒有戴安全帽
But soon you find out that
但是很快的你就發現說
The number of hospitalized patients has decreased by 30%
住院的病人減少了三成
Death rate reduced by 56%
死亡率減少五成六
was very surprised
當時就是很吃驚
suddenly so much less
突然就少了這麼多
At the time, people thought it couldn't be prevented.
當時大家以為說這不可能有預防的
It turned out that the wards were all empty.
結果真的是病房都空掉了
A third of the wards are empty
三分之一的病房都空掉
So of course I was scolded by the MP
所以後來當然被議員罵了
There is no legal basis for saying this, just ban it casually
說這個也沒有法根據 隨便取締
They don't dare to catch it anymore
他們就不敢再抓了
then later
那麼後來
next
下一張
so in
所以在
Through the middle process I would have had many times
經過中間的過程 我本來有很多時代
I took it all off
我都把它拿掉了
this is a lot of process
這個很多的過程
Sometimes there's a parade, there's a Campan
有時候有遊行 有Campan
do everything
各方面的都做
even at public hearings
甚至在公聽會啦
in the legislature
在立法院
Very hard
很辛苦
after more than three years
當時經過三年多
Finally in 1997
終於在1997年
Passed on June 1, 1986
民國86年的6月1號通過
next
下一張
This is before the legislation
這個是立法前
You see this man is very smart
你看這個人滿聰明的
full of wisdom
滿有智慧的
next
下一張
This person is also good
這個人也不錯
He's the only one here
這裡面只有他帶
next
下一張
At that time began to ban
那時候開始取締
one day
一天就開出
More than 10,000 slippery eggs
一萬多張的滑蛋
the whole country
全國
next
下一張
you see it's been a few days
你看就過了幾天
become like this
就變成這樣
next
下一張
This can still be legal
這個還可以保留法行
when i speak abroad
我在國外講的時候
I talked about this
我講到說這個
i thought it was a joke
我本來以為是開玩笑
Then someone really got up and asked me
結果有人真的起來問我說
how do you promote
那你們怎麼推動
animal hard hat
動物的安全帽
i can't tell
我也講不出來
next
下一張
this is in Taichung
這個是在台中
look at this
你看這個
it's over 100%
它已經超過100%了
Then you see so much of this one
那這一張你看這麼多
I only see a hard hat that looks like a fake
我只看到一個好像假的安全帽
So this effect is pretty good
所以這個效果還蠻好的
then let's see how it turns out
那我們看看結果如何
next
下一張
you see usually start here
你看平常從這裡開始
this is taipei
這是台北市的
It turned out to be at 7300
原來都在7300
around 7400
7400左右
Then the motor vehicle accident injury
那麼機動車事故傷害
just keep falling
就這樣一直掉
Fall here and leave around 4300
掉到這裡剩下4300左右
Recently dropped to around 3600
最近又掉到3600左右
More recent what CBL
最近更多的什麼CBL
everything is coming
什麼通通都來了
so
所以
The final proof is
最後的證明就是
it helps
它有幫忙的
some people asked me
有些人就問我說
Is that because the number of cars is decreasing?
那是不是車子在減少
my next one
我下一張
No car has been increasing
沒有車子一直在增加
Now it has reached 14 million
現在已經到1400萬輛
Increased by 82% over the past 10 years
增加了82%這10年間
Then the population also increases
那麼人口也是增加
11% increase
增加11%
Admission increased by 10.5%
入場增加10.5%
But the death rate dropped by 51%
但是死亡率掉了51%
next
下一張
This is very important to our public health
這個是我們公共衛生很重要的
potential loss of life
就是潛在生命損失
Very helpful especially for this young person
特別對這個年紀輕的人很有幫忙
so i believe
所以我相信
not only saved a lot of people
不但是救了很多人
but saved the young man
但是救了年輕人
this is more important
這個更重要
next
下一張
You can see that we have been
你可以看到原來我們一直
This is nearly 30 years
這個將近30年
Both are the third of the top ten babies
都是十大十嬰的第三位
suddenly in that year
突然就在那一年
dropped to fourth place
就掉到第四位
fifth place
第五位
sixth place
第六位
Hope to catch up with diabetes to the seventh place soon
希望很快可以再追過糖尿病到第七位
next
下一張
This is where we put the whole
這個是我們在把整個
last july
今年去年七月
rewrite the whole
把整個再寫一遍
you can see this
你可以看到這個
This is the case with increased locomotive maneuvers
這是機車機動增加的情形
next
下一張
In front, T1 to T4 are all doing life-saving.
前面就是T1到T4都是在做救命的
I will talk about some functional issues later
我後面就講一些功能上的問題
Since then, almost all researches have focused on functional
那以後的研究幾乎都是在為功能
Efforts to improve these functions
為了改善這些功能來努力
I might speak faster
我這個可能講快一點
Because this place is still full of deep
因為這個地方還滿深的
next
下一張
So what is this called a concussion?
那這個是什麼叫做腦震盪
or mild traumatic brain injury
或者是輕度的腦外傷
That is to say, the unconscious time should not exceed 30 minutes.
就是說昏迷的時間不要超過30分鐘
This is the definition of the US Department of Defense
這個是美國國防部的定義
The same goes for its altered consciousness
它的意識改變也是一樣
no more than 20 hours
就是不超過20小時
Then there is memory loss within 24 hours
然後有記憶的喪失是24小時以內
while scores are 13 to 15
同時分數是13到15
The most important one is
最重要的一個就是
Mild traumatic brain injury is a CT scan
輕度腦外傷就是做了CT scan
are all
都是
can't see things can't see hurt
看不到東西的 看不到傷害的
But although I can't see the damage
但是雖然看不到傷害呢
It still has sequelae, let me tell you
它還是有後遺症 我跟各位講
next
下一張
Why does everyone attach so much importance to this
為什麼大家這麼重視這個叫做
Mild The S just now means serious
輕度 剛才那個S就是嚴重
M means mild
M就是輕度的意思
He said
他說
Nearly 20% of the soldiers
有將近20%的士兵呢
sent to iraq afghanistan
派到伊拉克阿富汗
After coming back, they still have this symptom 20%
回來以後都有這個症狀 20%
What about in the Marine Corps?
那麼在海軍陸戰隊呢
This is somewhere in Afghanistan
這個在阿富汗一個地方呢
92% of his injuries are not likely to be brain injuries.
他有92%的受傷 倒不容易是腦的受傷
Then what
然後呢
This armed vehicle
這種武裝的車子
there's no way or no way to
甚至沒有辦法 或是沒有辦法對
This blast wave especially
這種blast wave 特別是
low low frequency wave
低 low frequency 的wave
damage to the brain
對腦的傷害
So it is very simple to say
所以很簡單的就是說
if you are a soldier
如果你是一個軍人
there's an explosion nearby
附近有個爆炸
you have never been hurt before
你以前沒有受過傷
But 60% of people still have this
但是60%的人還是會有這種
mild brain injury
輕度的腦傷
What if there were more than four times before?
如果以前有四次以上的呢
100% will have this symptom
百分之百都會有這個症狀
Symptoms come out
症狀出來
so this
所以這個
Go back to the American soldier
對美國這個軍人回去
very serious
非常嚴重
So he asked several countries
所以他就請求幾個國家
Let's do it together and see what he said too
一起來做看看他也是看說
Which country has done the most research
哪個國家研究做的最多
So we also join in this study
所以我們也一起加入這個研究裡面
So for this mild brain trauma
那麼對這個輕度的腦創傷
In fact we also have many
事實上我們也很多
We're just different types of injuries
我們只是不同型態的受傷
But also very mild
但是也是輕度的非常多
Many have never seen a doctor at all.
很多根本就沒看過病
But he has many symptoms
但是他就很多症狀都出來
next
下一張
i forgot or forgot to tell this
我忘記還是忘記講這個
why is the voice hoarse
為什麼聲音會沙啞
right no
對對不是
not me mild brain trauma
不是我輕度腦創傷
because I was
是因為我那時候
pushing hard hat
在推動安全帽
I remember that time
那個時候我記得那個時候
The Director of Nursing is
照護處的處長就是
Yu Yumei Professor Yu
余玉美 余教授
And Lai Meishu, Professor Lai
還有賴美淑 賴教授
two are government
兩個是政府
He arranged a lot of speeches for me
他就排了好多演講給我
what to talk about
到處去講什麼
Kaohsiung Taichung Countryside
高雄 台中 鄉下
Talk about everything Three Gorges
什麼都講 三峽
There are hundreds of games
幾百場有
He just wants to push this hard hat
他就為了要推動這個安全帽
I was a scholar at that time
那時候我是學者
Scholar's speech is enough
學者講話就很夠力
talk now no one will listen
現在講話沒人會聽
This official is useless
這個官員就沒有用了
nothing works
什麼都沒有用
was a scholar
那時候是學者
So academics I talk about hard hats all day long
所以學者我一天到晚都在講安全帽
it's important very important
這很重要 非常重要
I always take that
我到時候都是拿著那個
a preserved egg tofu
一個皮蛋豆腐
Then put it on the ground and show them
然後就塞到地上給他們看
Broken in a plastic bag
塑膠袋裝著 碎掉的
That's how it was done back then
那時候弄的就是這樣
Preserved egg tofu
皮蛋豆腐
So talk every day for a long time
所以天天講講講久了
Afterwards, the voice killed the teeth
後來這個聲音就殺牙
can't come back
回不來了
As long as there are too many lectures in the course, it will start to kill the itch
只要課程課一講多就開始殺癢
This is the sequelae
這個是後遺症
not a brain injury
不是腦瘡傷的
The main symptom is anemia red disorder
主要的症狀就是貧紅障礙
Look at this MTBI poor red disorder
你看這個MTBI 貧紅障礙
Because of Nell's connection to the cerebellar concussion.
因為內爾跟小腦的震盪的關係
headache hearing loss tinnitus
頭痛 聽力障礙 耳鳴
or cognitive impairment
或者是認知障礙
So far there is no good treatment
到目前還沒有什麼好的治療
nothing good so far
到目前還沒有什麼好
next
下一張
So this is four countries in the world
所以這個是全世界四個國家
Israel is also a country that often explodes
以色列也是常常爆炸的國家
Motor vehicle accidents in Taiwan
台灣是機動車事故
famous a lot serious
很有名 很多 很嚴重
Sweden is one that is equal to less
瑞典是一個等於是比較少的
it is the least harmed country in the world
它是世界上傷害最少的國家
So they are more like a country-by-country study
所以它們比較等於是個個國家的研究
All directions, I will pass quickly, the next one
各個方向 我就很快的過去 下一張
The diagnostic tool next
那 診斷的工具 下一張
Of course this patient must have
那當然這個病人一定要有
Inclusion and exclusion mean
inclusion跟exclusion就是說
Which ones can be in it? Others can’t. The next one
哪些可以在裡面 其他不行的 下一張
Then this is the basic information, about 190 or so
那麼這個是基礎資料 大概190幾個
Because of this why the charge is less
因為這個 為什麼收的比較少
Because of this the first patient has to agree to the second
因為這個 第一個病人要同意 第二個呢
Once he does these tests
他一做這些測試
It's all harmless
都是沒有什麼傷害的
It's just a questionnaire, what an hour?
就是問卷啊 什麼一個鐘頭
Everyone will still avoid it
大家都還是都會避之有恐不及
But some because doing it helps him
不過有些因為做出來對他有幫忙
so he will participate
所以他會參與
the next one
那下一張
Then you can see why this happened
那這個可以看到 這個發生的原因
About 50% of car accidents now
現在車禍大概50%
Others are falls or injuries
其他是跌落 或者是傷害
next
下一張
Then we used 14 tables
那我們用了14個表格
This is all countries in the world
這個是世界各國一起
Four countries synchronized
四個國家同步
Doing this four, it's four tables
在做這個四個,是四個表格
The next one, I don't mention this
下一張,我這個都不提
What are the main symptoms we see
我們看到主要的症狀是哪些
These are just the thirty types I just mentioned
這些只是我剛才講的三十種的
Of the ten, the most common is dizziness
其中的十種,最常見的還是頭暈
Dizziness, dizziness after a mild injury
頭暈,輕度的受傷以後就頭暈
headache, sleep disturbance
頭痛,睡眠障礙
Now more and more data prove that
現在越來越多的資料證明
Sleep disturbance linked to brain injury
睡眠障礙跟腦受傷很有關係
mildly cause
輕度的就會引起
memory impairment
記憶障礙
And I can't concentrate
還有注意力沒辦法集中
These five are the most common
這五個是最常見的
This is the first accused stage
這是第一個accused stage
When impromptu, the next
即興起的時候,下一張
After six stars, you are following it
六星起以後,你在追蹤它
or headache, the most common
還是頭痛,最常見
Dizziness, now it's a headache, just dizziness
頭暈,現在變成頭痛,剛才是頭暈
Then memory impairment, turn it up a bit
然後記憶障礙,調到高一點
then follow this
然後接著這個
can't concentrate
注意力沒辦法集中
and
跟
sleep disorder
就是睡眠障礙
next
下一張
Then let's see what if it's dizzy?
那我們看呢 如果是頭暈來看呢
There are a few forms I think this one I'll make soon
有幾個表格 我想這個我就很快了
Avaka scale, Dhi, Y, Bd scale
AVC scale, DHI, VAI, BDI scale
These are all able to detect this
這幾個都有可以測出這個
Dissidence is dizziness
Dissidence 就是頭暈的
Headache is one
頭痛呢 就是一個
Anxious VAI scale helps
焦慮的VAI scale 有幫忙
next
下一張
What about sleep disorders?
睡眠障礙呢
This VAI BDI
這個VAI BDI
Here are some tables of depression
這是憂鬱症的一些表
Also the Digitspan of this memory
另外這個記憶的Digitspan
These few are related to the next one
這個幾個有關係 下一張
What about memory? These two
那麼對記憶力呢 這兩個
DHI and Digitspan
DHI跟Digitspan
these two
這兩個
So now many scales can be measured
所以現在很多的scale 都可以測出
some very mild symptoms
一些很輕微的症狀
This is what several of our countries are doing together.
這個是我們幾個國家一起在做進行的
Then I also took these medicines at the same time
那麼同時也用了這幾個藥
Here are some medicines
這是幾個藥
Well, we're almost in sync and venting too
那麼我們幾乎呢 同步也發洩
The previous medicine helped with dizziness
前面的藥對頭暈有幫忙
Topamax was originally an antiepileptic drug
Topamax原來是抗癲的藥
Helpful for this depression
對這個depression有幫忙
Serenna is helpful to designus
Serenna對designus有幫忙
So take it slow
所以慢慢的對這種
Because there was no special medicine on the mild head part
因為原來輕度的頭部位上沒什麼特別藥物
everyone has been looking for
大家一直在找
Find out if there is any medicine that can help these symptoms
找看看有沒有什麼藥物可以對這些症狀能夠有幫忙
especially long-term symptoms
特別是長期的症狀
next
下一張
The second is to use the functional
第二個就是用功能性的
Resonance scan
這個詞合共振掃描
functional MRI to test memory
functional MRI來做記憶的測試
this is also very important
這個也非常重要
next
下一張
For example, this is called
譬如說這個就是叫做
is walking memory
就是walking memory
It's you who saw these faces
就是你看了這幾個臉
which one have you seen
哪一個你曾經看過的
just think about it
你就去想
seen this
這個看過
He will test you again when you are using your brain
你在用腦的時候他就再給你測
Test your activity
測你的activity
next
下一張
Then this is one back
然後這個是one back
Just look at a number and then look at it for the first time
就看一個數目以後第一次再看看
Whichever ones you have seen, you can point them out
有哪幾個你看過你就把它點出來
After seeing this, press your hand
這看過了就手壓一下
Then you are called walk in memory
那你這個叫做walk in memory
one back
one back
two back is
two back就是
I have to remember more
又要記憶更多了
How did you compare to last time?
就是上一次的你比較怎麼樣
three back is
three back就是
How much do you remember from the last time
再上一次的你記得多少
wow he's about to think
哇他就要去想
Think about this kind of one back two back three back
那這種one back two back three back來想
next
下一張
then you can see
那你可以看到
one back normal
one back正常的
two back three back
two back three back
he uses more brainpower
他用更多的腦力
But this wounded person
但是這種受傷的人
he is bad
他就差了
he's all bad
他整個都差了
poor memory
記憶的功能差了
next
下一張
then you too
那麼你也是一樣
if you cut it off
如果你把它剪掉的話
You can see the wounded people almost
你可以看到受傷的人幾乎
When it comes to two back three back
到了two back three back的時候
he can't use anything
他用不出什麼東西來
next
下一張
Then this is after progress
那麼這個是有進步以後
this is the initial stage
這個是初期
When I was first injured
初期剛剛受傷的時候
you can see this
你可以看到這個
2BG reduced to 1BG
2BG減到1BG
Or 3BG reduced to 2BG
或是3BG減到2BG
are relatively poor
都是比較差的
but
但是呢
about 6 weeks later
差不多6個星期以後
You can see it's coming back a lot
你可以看到又回來很多了
next
下一張
So
那麼
This is called Rest in state
這個叫Rest in state
functional MRI
functional MRI
this one has to close the eyes
這個必須閉著眼睛
can't think about anything
不能想什麼事情
This is pretty difficult
這個蠻難的
and then can't fall asleep
然後又不能睡著
It's also very complicated to do this
這個做這個也是很複雜
It's been a long time
這個時間還蠻久的
next
下一張
all the world does is see
全世界做的就是看
what is this looking at
這個是看什麼
connectivity
connectivity
In fact, the mind of the brain
事實上腦的思想
are all interrelated
都是有互相關聯性
It's all interconnected
這個都是互相關聯性
There are about 8 places in the world that do it
全世界做的大概有8個地方
I won't mention this
這個我就不提了
next
下一張
We did about these 4 places
我們做的大概這4個地方
You can see this is normal
你可以看到這個是正常的
Both sides are pretty good. Connectivity is not bad.
這兩邊都蠻 Connectivity 都還不錯
Connectivity of two brains after injury
受傷以後兩個大腦的 Connectivity
Activity Connectivity is bad
Activity Connectivity 就差了
next
下一張
this is the same
這個也是一樣
Another place with AC
另外一個地方AC的地方
This will get worse
這個以後都變差了
next
下一張
This IPL is getting worse
這個 IPL 都變差了
this is getting worse
這個都變差了
next
下一張
This IPC has also become worse.
這個 IPC 這個也都變差了
So the whole thing looks like this is pretty obvious for
所以整個看起來這個是對於很明顯的
functional connectivity
functional connectivity
All in Resident State Network
都在 Resident State Network
It's obviously getting worse
是很明顯的變差了
next
下一張
that's all we want to say
我們就想說這個
took a lot of medicine
用了很多藥
Some help some not necessarily
有些有幫忙有些不一定
Most recent from 2008
最近從2008年
I am reporting by the way
我這是順便報告
It's Felici
就是Felici 這個人
Report a rather shocking statement that
報告一個蠻震驚的就是說
For this use this TTCS
對於這個用這個TTCS
TTCS
TTCS
So how about stimulating the brain?
那麼來刺激這個腦部呢
Find out about this R-CIMER
發現對這R-CIMER
Or is there a
或者是對這個中風有
Motor neuritis can help
運動神經炎都有幫忙
then this doesn't hurt
那這個沒有什麼傷害
no harm so far
目前沒有什麼傷害
So we also made a few
所以我們也做了幾個
next
下一張
see if it helps
那看看有沒有幫忙
Just after the injury
就是受傷以後呢
You'll see it compared with
你會看到它有比較
scattered
散掉了
This activity suddenly dissipates
這個activity突然散掉
It seems to be better after finishing
做完好像都好了一些
next
下一張
this is the same
這個也是一樣
This patient is obviously
這個病人是明顯
Sometimes his memory improves
有時候他記憶有改善
But this one hasn't
不過這個呢還沒有
very mature
很成熟
just everyone now
只是大家現在
Only started coming out after 2008
2008年以後才開始出來
just use normal
就是用一般的
very light
很輕
very small stimulus
非常微小的刺激而已
next
下一張
I won't mention this
這個我就不提了
then in addition
那麼另外
the third is
第三個就是
What I want to tell you is
我要跟大家提的就是
It is very simple called BioMarker
就是很簡單的叫做BioMarker
BioMarker is
BioMarker就是
after you get hurt
在你在受傷以後
There must be a component in the blood or spinal cord that will try out
血中或者是脊髓意中一定有一個成分會試出來
will rise
會高起來
Then we are looking for the most ideal BioMarker
那我們就是要找這個最理想的BioMarker
What is called BioMarker?
叫做BioMarker叫什麼生物標誌
This biomarker is now the world's
這個生物標誌現在已經是全世界
This Vice President Chen is in prison
這個陳副院長是聽監的
But it's more complicated in the brain
但是這個在腦部比較複雜
especially after traumatic brain injury
尤其腦外傷以後
next
下一張
then we are looking for
那我們就在找
This must be the most ideal BioMarker
這個一定是最理想的BioMarker
must be easy to get
一定是很容易去拿到的
As far as the patient is concerned, don't suffer too much
就病人不要太suffer
Put a tube in your head to get it
放個管子在腦子裡面才拿得到
it doesn't make sense
那就沒有意義
So normal blood can be seen
所以一般的血液都可以看得到的就好了
then it has diagnostic value
那麼它有診斷的價值
It is also helpful for the queen
對欲後也有幫忙
From BioMarker you can see that
從BioMarker就可以看到說
what will happen to this patient
這個病人將來會怎麼樣
hope so
希望能夠這樣
Will the memory come back?
記憶會不會恢復
what will happen
會不會怎麼樣
Will motor function return?
運動功能會不會恢復
Then there is a therapeutic effect
那麼有治療上的效果
this is very important
這個是很重要
the most important thing
最重要呢
it can follow its severity
它能夠跟著它的嚴重度
or the progression of its time
或者是它的時間的進展
can show its composition
可以顯出它的成分
say it's progressing
譬如說它在進步
We saw that Marker come down
我們就看到那個Marker下來
I knew what would happen to this patient
我就知道說這個病人結果會怎麼樣
next
下一張
So we have a clinical pathway
所以我們有一個臨床路徑
Decision Tree
Decision Tree
Decision Tree means
Decision Tree就是說
My wine room has a slight
我這個酒室有比較輕微的
10% serious
10%嚴重的
Then some cut and some don't
然後有些開刀有些不開刀
The last 95% live
最後95%活的
1% of these living people are vegetative
這些活的裡面有一%是植物人
4% are severely disabled
有4%是嚴重的殘障
7%
7%
then 80%
那麼有80%
3% recovery
3%恢復
what about this
那這個呢
Let's look at his cognitive function at the end
在最後我們再看看他的認知功能
psychological function
心理上的功能
or physiological functions, etc.
或是生理上的功能等等
What about from this process?
那從這個過程裡面呢
We can use BioMarker to analyze him
我們就可以用BioMarker來分析他
next
下一張
This is what we are doing now
這個是我們目前呢
We report a lot of BioMarkers all over the world
我們全世界報告的BioMarker非常多
that this
那這個
We are more commonly used is S100B
我們比較常用的是S100B
GFAP's NSE and Apple E
GFAP的NSE跟Apple E這幾個
next
下一張
so recently
那麼最近呢
we found a
我們發現有一個
ETK
ETK
I don’t think I need to talk about this ETK anymore
這ETK我想就不用再講這些了
then this
那麼這個
right
對
A lot of what we want is met
很多我們要的都符合
next
下一張
I don't think I need the next one
這個我想就不用下一張
for example
譬如說
he can control
他可以左右
injured on the right
右邊受傷
that will make it stronger
那就會搞強
Gao Qiang on the right hand
右邊手上高強
Then Impact 2
那麼Impact 2
Heavier damage is deeper
比較重的傷害就比較深
this is the same
這個也是一樣
it can be divided left and right
它可以分左右
next
下一張
even it can
甚至呢它可以
It knows both weight and strength
重量 力量它都知道
Same as this S100 X10
一樣 這個S100 X10
Of course there is one, but it's not so clear
當然也有一點 但是不是那麼清楚
also a little
也有一點
then even in
那麼甚至在
When Impact is heavy
Impact比較重的時候呢
When the strength is greater
力量比較大的時候呢
it is heavier
它就比較重 下一張
Then look at its timing, timing
那你看它的時間序 時序
time this is GFAP
時間 這個是GFAP
This is Acting
這個是Acting
then look at this
那你看這個呢
One hour Three hours Six hours One day Ten days
一小時 三小時 六小時 一天 十天
Then what
然後呢
When the brain swelling starts to disappear
它這個腦腹腫開始消的時候
it just falls
它就掉下來
so for this time
所以對這個時間
Timing Severity
時序 嚴重度
help in every way
各方面都有幫忙
next
下一張
so what do we think
所以我們認為呢
this may be a
這個也許是一個
Effective BioMarker
有效的BioMarker
It this Rapid Change
它這個Rapid Change
There are T-Shows Organization Specific
有T-Shows組織Specific
have a diagnosis
有診斷
In addition
另外呢
it can know the severity
它可以知道嚴重度
And Time Course
還有Time Course
and easy to get
而且很容易拿到
So maybe a Candidate BioMarker
所以可能是一個Candidate BioMarker
TBI
TBI
This is the direction we are trying to find
這個就是我們努力在找的一個方向
next
下一張
So
那麼
new drug development
新藥的開發
Of course, the development of this new drug has nothing to do with BioMarker
當然這個新藥的開發跟BioMarker
very relevant
很有關係
With the BioMarker just mentioned
跟剛才講的BioMarker
next
下一張
Then this is our cooperation with Academia Sinica
那這是我們跟中研院合作的
us
我們
This one from Beijing Medical University
北醫的這個
School of Pharmacy cooperates with Academia Sinica
藥學院跟中研院合作
Scream comes out a lot
Scream出來很多的
Red are neuroprotective drugs
紅色都是有神經保護的藥物
Then we chose a program called Emo-Dim
那我們選取了一個叫做Emo-Dim
Emo-Dim
Emo-Dim
next
下一張
then this is
那麼這個是
This is an emodin
這個就是一個大黃素
But a Compound
但是一個Compound
next
下一張
Then we start from the first day
那我們從第一天
just give him the next one
就給他下一張
You can see that this is the taste of water maize
你可以看到這個是water maize的taste
A test on the memory of mice
對老鼠的記憶的測驗
It can be seen that this is injured and it will become like this
可以看到這個是受傷的以後變成這樣
this is
這個是
I used this emodim and it seems to be helpful
用了這個emodim有看起來是有幫忙
Of course in the end with
當然最後還是跟
Even better than this sham
甚至比這個sham還好一點
is to control
就是控制
You can see in this process
你看這個過程裡面你就可以看到
emodim
emodim
ETK, GFAP, Connecting
ETK, GFAP, Connecting
These indicators are very obvious
這幾個指標都很明顯的
lower than the original
比原來下降
Especially ETK with obvious
特別是ETK跟明顯
I think this is from days
我想這個都是從第幾天
fourth day, seventh day
第四天,第七天
I think
我想
It is of course better to look at several indicators at the same time
同時看幾個指標當然是更好
This bio mark is better
這個bio mark更好
But this proves that the medicine
但是這個證明這個藥
to this
對這個
Then the protection function is there
然後的保護功能是有的
So now let's develop BioMarker first
所以現在呢先發展BioMarker
Then see the effect of this medicine
然後再看這個藥的效果
This is also a good direction
這個是也是一個很好的方向
next
下一張
So we also think that ETK is
所以我們也是認為ETK是
With this severity is a good BioMarker
跟這個嚴重度是一個很好的BioMarker
In addition this EmoDIM is
另外這個EmoDIM是
Helpful for this too
對這個也有幫忙
next
下一張
so probably
所以大概是
These are the ones we are doing research on
這個幾個就是我們在做研究
And we still have a few
另外我們還有幾個還沒有
The result hasn't come out yet
結果還沒出來
just a few sleep cycles
就是幾個睡眠的週期
Called Sercadium Regen
叫Sercadium Regen
There are also some genetic tests
另外還有一些基因的測試
Genetic testing probably won't make sense to everyone
基因測試大概大家聽了也聽不下去
But in this gene
不過這個基因裡面
Many of them also affect the prognosis of patients
很多也是影響到病人的愈後
this is
這個是
the whole process
整個的過程
what about the future
那未來怎麼辦
next
下一張
We'll probably all be doing this in the future
未來過去我們大概都在做這個
This is what we just saw
這個就是我們剛剛看到的
They are all doing life-saving work
都是在做救命的工作
Then the future is us
那將來呢就是我們
it keeps falling
是一直在掉下來
keep falling
一直在掉下來
In the future, it is to improve the function
那將來就是要做功能的改善
At the same time the next one
同時呢下一張
then what to do at the same time
那麼同時也要做什麼
economic benefit
也要做經濟效益
Then this is Chen
那麼這個是陳
Vice President Chen
陳副院長
He hosted a program called BioSignature
他做主持的一個program叫BioSignature
The most important thing here is the BioMarkers
這裡面呢最重要的還是這個BioMarkers
add this
加上這個
Cost-effectiveness
成本效益
If it is possible to put this
如果能夠把這個
fell down
掉下來呢
to this
對這個
Finance can also help
財務也有幫忙的話
To this Cost Effective
對這個Cost Effective
that's even better
那就更好了
what about the future, of course i think about this
那麼將來呢當然我想這個
direction is very good
方向是非常好
next
下一張
let's look at this
那我們看一下這個
whole traumatic brain
整個腦創傷的
Health insurance data files
健保的資料檔
you can see
你可以看到
Our patients have been decreasing just like what we did just now
我們病人是跟著我們剛才那個一樣是一直在減少
has been decreasing
一直在減少
But for the next one, his fee will continue to be high
但是下一張,他的費用還是繼續的高
So this is also the direction we have to work hard
所以這個也是我們要努力的方向
next
下一張
Then this is also a patient in the outpatient clinic.
那這個也是門診的一個病人
That probably cost us a lot.
那大概我們花掉的費用還是很高
So this is also a heavy burden for the country
所以這個也是國家一個很重的負擔
Maybe we can specialize in patients with these sequelae
也許我們可以特別是這些後遺症的病人
also have a great influence
影響的也很大
next
下一張
so i think the future
所以我想將來呢
we will continue to do some
我們會繼續做一些
to this BioSignature
對這個BioSignature
What I was talking about just now is
剛才在講的這個是
BioMaker plus a study of Cos effective
BioMaker再加上Cos effective的一個研究
Then continuing this will be of greater help to mankind.
那繼續這個對人類會有更大的幫忙
next
下一張
then this is
那這個是
This is Chen Yun
這個是陳雲
Chen Yun is the team led by Lea Hardware
陳雲是跟Lea Hardware所領導的團隊
next
下一張
so
所以
The whole conclusion is that
整個的結論呢就是說
what about our research
我們的研究呢
Do it all the way from T1, T2, T3, T4
從T1,T2,T3,T4一直做
Finally, we improved the function
最後我們做到功能的改善
In addition to saving lives
除了生命的挽救以外
Finally, we still need to improve this function, the next one
最後還是要改善這個功能,下一張
We are currently working on many more
目前我們在進行的還有更多的
This is also a clinical trial
這個也是有一個臨床的試驗
This is made by a manor
這個是有一個莊院是做的
He uses this in the neurological function of the flying belly
他用這個在神經功能的飛腹
very good on animals
非常好在動物上面
So this we will study in the future
所以這個我們將來要研究
Is it helpful to people, the next one
對人是不是有幫忙,下一張
and we will continue
還有繼續的我們會在做
With the US National Institutes of Health
跟這個美國的國家衛生院
And some of our institutions in Taiwan
還有我們臺灣的一些機構
Many institutions have eight topics in progress
很多機構有八個題目在走
In fact, probably this
事實上大概這個都是
Also are some nerve restoration NUROProtective
也都是一些神經的恢復NUROProtective
How to do nerve protection
怎麼樣來做神經的保護
next
下一張
This is what we are grateful to the team
這個是我們很感謝團隊
There are also various Supporting Agents
還有各個的Supporting Agent
So I guess the whole process goes like this
那麼我想整個過程就是這樣
This is a lot
這個很多的
a hard hat push
一個安全帽的推動
In fact, it is supported by many studies
其實是很多的研究來支撐的
So research may be a
所以研究也許是一個
A very important process of a legislation
一個立法的一個很重要的一個過程
I want to simply report to here
我想簡單的報告到這裡
Thanks
謝謝
We thank the old director
我們謝謝舊署長
give us this wonderful speech
給我們這個很精采的這個演講
What to say from foreign research
說怎麼樣從外商的研究
pushed until legislation
一直推動到立法
and how to make his voice affected
然後怎麼樣讓他的聲音受到影響
Then everyone's lifespan can be reduced
然後大家的壽命可以減少
In fact, you can see
那實際上大家可以看到
Now foreign businessmen have to pay gold coins to the government
現在外商對政府要付出的金幣
also quite a lot
也是相當的多
I really appreciate the care he has done for the health of our people.
真的是很謝謝他為我們全民所做的健康上所做的這個照顧
that now
那現在
After the Soviet Party finished speaking, I don’t know if you have any questions and would like to ask for leave. Please come here.
蘇黨講完了不曉得各位有沒有什麼問題要請假來這邊請
I want to thank the Soviet Party today
我要謝謝蘇黨今天
give us then
給我們那麼
That's more information
那多了資料
I want to ask the Soviet Party
我要請問蘇黨說
The emphasis is on the brain, but you didn’t mention traditional Chinese medicine in your speech just now.
那強調大腦你那你剛才演講就是沒有提到中醫
that of Chinese medicine
中醫方面那個
TCM assistance in this regard
中醫在這方面的協助
is that
那是不是
please that
請你那個
Then explain it, okay?
那說明一下好不好
thanks for that
謝謝那個
TCM we probably
中醫我們大概
more importantly
比較重要的是
From the research of traditional Chinese medicine, the emodin mentioned just now
從中藥的研究剛才也提到的像大黃素這些
So
那麼
Of course, the way of Chinese medicine is general
當然中醫的方式一般
more acute
比較急性的
Or in Western medicine more
還是在西方的醫學比較多
We don't have a deep understanding of traditional Chinese medicine.
那中醫我們倒沒有很深入去了解
Generally, we cooperate with traditional Chinese medicine
一般我們都是跟中藥中醫的合作待會
all in Chinese medicine
都在中藥上
Aspects of these restorations to memory function
對記憶功能這些恢復的方面
probably like this
大概這樣
Ask Director Qiu
請教邱署長
Today I am very convinced to hear the director's lecture
今天我很服氣聽到署長這個講座
Because I used to crash
因為我曾經那個摔車
I mean the motorcycle fell off
就是說摩托車摔下來
That moment was almost a few seconds
那瞬間差不多有幾秒鐘
not at all for a few seconds
幾秒鐘完全不
i.e. completely blank
就是說完全空白
then wake up
然後醒來的時候
I just feel my head is so heavy
只是覺得頭好重好重
At that time, it was very heavy to wear a hard hat.
那個時候有戴安全帽好重好重
that until today
那到今天
but at that time
但是當時
I don't feel like I didn't go to the hospital
就不覺得怎麼樣也沒有上醫院
Then you just mentioned that this has
那你剛有提到說這個有
just say how much
就說有多
After 30%, it will be easier to change the time card
30%以後會比較容易換時代證
I've been doing this for almost a few years
我這個差不多幾年了
then you pass
那你過關了
almost ten years
差不多十十年了
Cleared
過關了
Will there be sequelae in the future?
以後會不會說有後遺症出現
It all happened a year or two later, some will happen again
都算發生了一兩年以後有些還會發生
But after a while it rarely happens again
但是過了這一段時間很少再發生
rare
很少
That is to say later
那就是說以後
Is memory affected
記憶有沒有受到影響
my memory is not very good
我記憶不是很好
but not serious
但是還沒有嚴重到
That is to say, it is still possible to read
就是說還是可以閱讀了
can still learn
還是可以學習
That is not bad
那還好
you have passed
你已經過關了
It should be passed
應該是過關了
Really will not advance the times in the future
真的以後不會提前時代
rare
很少
In our watch rarely happens again
在我們看了很少再發生
so
這樣
Some people have more than a year
有人到一年多還有
Very good
太好了
thank you so much
太感謝了
Thank you, Mr. Su, thank you
謝謝蘇長謝謝
an intro to me just forgot
對我剛剛忘記一個介紹
Our Professor Jiang Yongsai
一位我們這個蔣永塞教授
He is actually the soul of this study
他是其實這個研究的靈魂人物
Then when I go to Su, he is doing it now.
那我到蘇裡面現在都他在做
Thanks
謝謝
Lord, you just mentioned
主長 剛才你有講到
about alheimer's disease
有關到愛之海默症
Then this is now the biggest threat to our people
那這個現在是我們國民最大的威脅
Now the age of bottle gold has been increasing
現在瓶金年齡都一直在增加
Does your field cover this part?
那你的領域有沒有涵蓋這一部分
we are surgeons
我們是外科醫生
Most of that is done by physicians
那大部分那個是內科醫生在做
but this
不過這個
his current base
他現在的基轉
more and more clear
越來越清楚
But still not completely Clear
但是還是不是完全Clear
but it is becoming clearer
但是越來越清楚
Or I just had a lot of it
還是我剛剛裡面很多的
BioMarket has something to do with that
BioMarket跟那個都有關係
Maybe Director Jiang has no idea about this
也許蔣主任有沒有對這個
What comment does R-Type have?
R-Type有什麼comment
Just according to the latest statistics
就是按照最近的統計的話
That is to say, to create a
就是說在說造成一個
The origin of disability
失因症的原來
old trauma is caused
老外傷是造成
one issued by early tibet
早期西藏發出的一個
So basically speaking, the quality that the teacher likes
所以基本上講這個老師喜歡的質
better not get hurt
最好是不要受傷
another one
另外一個
In addition to talking about the severity of his injuries
除了講他受傷的多重度之外
We are still in the number
我們還要處於次數
more times
次數越多的話
Of course the brain will be
當然腦子將來
means we bad chance
就是說我們不良機會
In fact, we used to have neurology diseases
其實我們曾經神經內科的病
But he suffered from trauma
但是他因為外傷引起的
Now it is getting more and more attention all over the world
現在越來越受到全世界的重視
but it's normal now
但是現在很平常
our this
我們這個
The main forest six community industry will encounter this problem
主林六社產產都會碰到這個問題
old age
年紀就大了
all have this phenomenon
都有這種現象
sorry
對不起
After joining
之後插班了
I just raised my hand and didn't get clicked
剛才舉手沒有被點到
I'm at a community college promoting
我是在社區大學在推廣
Lin Jingtang, a teacher of memory promotion and prevention, gave a speech
記憶力推廣預防的老師林警堂發言
i have two questions for the dean
我有兩個問題要請教書長
The first one is that just now we talked about
第一個就是說剛才有談到說
during that treatment
在那個治療的過程當中
will do this
會有做這個
farming or raising
農養或養的方面的施作
But from the inside of the antioxidant machine inside Professor Lin Tiansong
但是從那個林天宋教授裡面的抗氧化機的裡面
he mentioned a very important thing
他有提到一件很重要的事情
He said that in the process of first aid, especially in the ambulance
他說在急救的過程當中尤其在救護車上
He often gives an injection of that SOD first
他經常會先打一針那個SOD
The kind of potion that resists oxidation or polarizes beauty
抗氧化或極化美的那種藥劑
It means that after the epidemic prevention, his future brain
就是疫防以後他將來腦部
even if rescued
就算被救回來
But his cognitive function will be impaired
但是他的認知功能會有傷害
Because we all need to know that raising the brain is the biggest attack
因為我們大家要知道養對腦的攻擊是最大的
Because the oxidizer is
因為氧化機對
That brain attack is the biggest
那個腦的攻擊最大這一點
this is the second question
這是第二個問題
The second question I have
第二個問題我曾經
During the teaching process, one of the students was also injured by a motorcycle
在教學過程當中曾經有學員一到一位也是摩托車受傷的
then he comes
那他來
When he told me about his condition, my master had already
跟我講說他的狀況的時候我大師已經
because of how he is i listen to him
因為他是怎麼樣的我聽他
Ask him to explain how he got hurt first
請他先說明怎麼受傷的時候我就
estimate a little
稍微推估一下說
You are probably missing the back of your head
你很可能是後腦少找不定
because he has a symptom
因為他有一個症狀
that is
就是說
May have been touched all night
可能是整夜當下有受到碰及
cortical nerve
皮質的那個神經
Is there a large area of ​​local fusion or something?
是不是有很大面積的局部的融合之類的
I don't know
這我不太清楚
But he produced a phenomenon
不過他產生一個現象
He just creates some mutual
他就是會產生一些互相
or Internet
或者叫互聯
In other words, I see Su Zhanglin now
換句話說就是我現在看到蘇掌林
Standing over there is not only one
站在那邊其實不是只有一個
maybe three maybe five
可能是三個可能是五個
while standing there
同時站在那邊
Then he went to the capital department
然後他到京城科
each north each
各北部各
Because we live in Taoyuan
因為我們住桃園
Hospitals in Taoyuan in the northern regions have seen
北部各地區桃園的醫院都看過
Then the capital division
然後京城科
The ophthalmologist also went to see the workers are normal
那個眼科也去看過工人都正常
but can't explain
但是無法解釋
It's just that there is no way to treat it.
就是沒有辦法治療就對了
I use one I know of called
我是有用一個我所知道的一個叫做
Jeffson's Nice Law
Jeffson的那個尼士法
tell him to watch the moon at night
叫他跟晚上看月亮
Then use this method to host
然後用這個方法平時用主持
Let me see if the image can overlap again
把那個影像我看能不能再重疊回來
I don't know about that
那這一點我不曉得在
This medical base of that brain turns up
那個大腦的這個醫療基轉上面
Is there anything I can do to increase my knowledge
有什麼可以讓我增加知識的地方
the most important one
那最重要有一個
That is, the occupational therapy component
就是說 職能治療部分
to this part of the brain
對大腦的這一塊的這個婦緣
rarely treated
幾乎很少治療
I don't know if the Director can help in this regard
不曉得署長可不可以在這方面
give me some guidance thanks
給我一點導引 謝謝
This abdomen produced by treatment
治療產生的這個腹肆
usually
一般是這樣
because of some eye movement or
因為一些動眼或者是
external nerve injury
外懸神經受傷
or some kind of nerve injury
或什麼三四六對的神經受傷
that would have a negative impact
那有會產生負影
This long time see we long time see
這個長長見到 我們長長見到
Another phenomenon is
那另外一種現象就是
epileptic cancer
要做虐業的癲癌
Sadistic epilepsy, it produces hallucinations
虐業的癲癌 它會產生幻覺
or these
或是這些
It's a brain injury long enough to see
這是腦受傷有長見到
but i didn't see it
不過我沒有看到它
I don't know what this is
我不知道這種是
what kind of sobriety
到底是哪一種清醒
Then generally this
那麼一般這種
Causes can be found in most cases
腹肆大部分都可以找出原因
Doing a lot of testing can find
做很多的測試可以找到
Sometimes even use brainwaves
甚至有時候要用腦波
look inside the brain
看看腦部的到底
Is there any abnormal discharge
是不是有不正常的放電
Sometimes this abnormal discharge is
有時候這種不正常的放電都是
saw this for a while
一段時間看到這樣
but sometimes it doesn't
但是有時候又沒有
See if it's straight or long like this
看看它是正發還是長長這樣
So if there is a function
所以如果有功能
That 346 nerve injury
那個346對神經的受傷
that will also
那個也會
Also in the brainstem
另外在腦幹部位
Sometimes the brainstem
腦幹部位有時候那個
We're like at EW Nuclear
我們像在EW Nuclear
that will also
那個也會
That's where our third pair came out
就是我們第三對出來的地方
Like the brainstem or where it comes out
比如說腦幹或者出來的地方
where the primitive nucleus
那個原始神經核的地方
Injury can also produce this phenomenon
受傷也會產生這種現象
So there are quite a few reasons for it
所以它的原因還蠻多的
But the most important thing is to find out and find a way to treat it.
不過最重要還是查清楚才有辦法治療
Also the second is
另外第二個是
The problem with SODs
SOD的問題
I'll start with the neurorehabilitation
我先講那個神經復健
This is where Taiwan should work hard
這個是台灣要努力的地方
Because I was 30 or 20 years ago
因為我在30、20幾年前
probably soon
現在大概快
I forget my age now
我現在忘記自己年齡
bad memory
記憶不好
When I was in America about 20 years ago
大概20年前在美國的時候
i see its rehab center
我就看到它的rehab center
Very serious about brain sores
對腦瘡傷非常重視
Wow, all kinds of mental rehabilitation
哇 各種心理的復健
Function is neuro psychology
職能 就是neuro psychology
rehab rotation center
rehab rotation center
I am back in Taiwan and it is strange that our rehab is very simple
我回到台灣 奇怪 我們的rehab很簡單
I am not dividing any brain or anything
沒有在分什麼brain 什麼東西 沒有
But in that place whether you're in Texas
但是在那個地方 不管你在Texas
I see this brain rehab center everywhere in Pittsburgh
在Pittsburgh 在哪裡 我都看到這種brain rehab center
And a lot of people inside are once
而且裡面好多人 一次都是
Two, three or four people sit inside
二三四個人在裡面坐
So now there are several big centers in Taiwan
所以現在台灣也有幾個大的center
have already started, so the rehabilitation of the nerves
已經都開始 所以對神經的復健
we really have a lot of room to strengthen
我們真的有很多加強的空間
I want to thank you for specifically reminding this
我想很感謝你特別提醒這個
This is very important for Taiwan
這個非常重要 對台灣來講
is this good
這個是不是很好
so you can see it's not tv lately
所以你可以看到 最近不是電視
have seen one
有看到一個
This congressman was shot or what?
這個議員被槍傷還是怎麼樣
Afterwards, the skin returned to normal
後來恢復的肌膚都正常
This is a very good function
這個就是做了很好的職能
or mental rehabilitation
或者是心理復健
Mental rehabilitation is doing very well.
精神復健這個都做得非常好
there is a way to do this
才有辦法這樣子
I think you are very discerning
我想你很有眼見
As for this SOD in
至於這個SOD在
If you go in, call him
進去就給他打的話
This is generally not yet
這個一般現在還不是在
Inside GiLine
GiLine裡面
We said why do GiLine
我們說為什麼要做GiLine
the whole world or the whole country
就是全世界或者是全國
universally acknowledged fact
大家公認的一個事實
so maybe it helps
所以也許有幫忙
But if it's still in the research stage
但是如果還在研究階段的話
We don't put in GiLine
我們就不放入GiLine
Do not put in GiLine
不放入GiLine
you don't have to do it routinely
就不一定要例行去做它
But sometimes you can upgrade
但是有時候你可以升級
Whole trial if patient agrees
整體試驗如果病人同意
Can use
可以用
this i think this is
這個我想這個是
The current measures of this
目前這個的措施
GiLine not yet
GiLine還沒有
sorry
對不起
Of course the team leader
那當然組長
The leader compliments me like this
組長這樣誇我一下
i can't
我不能的
I need to change my major a little bit
要稍微把我的專業
don't report
就不報告一下
That is to say, in fact, after ten years in Taiwan,
就是說事實上我們台灣在過十年以後
The dementia or cognitive impairment
這個失智或者認知障礙
Even cognitive degeneration affects behavior
甚至於認知退化 影響行為
Then this kind of thing that affects the family
然後影響家庭的這種事情
i have dealt with a lot
我已經處理很多
So I feel that the future of Taiwan is really scary
所以我就覺得說台灣將來真的很可怕
The streets are full of old people who are afraid
到處滿街都是老人在怕
And I don't even know where my home is
而且都不知道自己家在哪裡
this is too much
這個已經太多了
the point is to say
那重點就是說
because in Europe
因為在歐洲方面
Now in Brain Science Education
現在在腦科學的教育
not wrong
不是講錯
This piece of adult education on the education of the brain
成人教育對腦的教育的這一塊
they have put education
他們已經把教育
Inclusion of adult education
對成人教育納入
A concept of health care
健保的一個觀念
This is the concept of health care
就是健康保健的這種觀念
Force the elderly to study as much as possible
強迫老人家盡量去學習
Prevent brain degeneration from affecting body degeneration
免得大腦退化 影響身體退化
Then this is hope
那這個是希望說
If Mr. Su says there is a chance
蘇長如果說有機會的話
Introduce this concept to our Taiwan
把這個觀念導引到我們台灣
lest in the next ten years there will be old people crawling everywhere
免得以後十年以後到處都是老人到處爬
The second situation is that
那第二個狀況就是說
Just now I mentioned this so-called prevention
剛才有講到這一個所謂的預防
The United States is now in
那美國現在已經在
There is a building next to the old house
建老房旁邊就有建
There is an old house next to the Jiansheng house
建生房旁邊就有建老房
they are now in person
他們現在對親自的
intimate self
親度的私自
Already did bad things
已經有做不良的事了
But our teacher in Taiwan said
可是我們台灣的老師講
I often participate in private
我常常參加私自
Private students learn many activities
私自生學會很多活動
Or Teacher Wang Peiling
或者王佩玲老師
often have some activities
常常有一些活動
I will send my DM
我去發我的DM
As a result, the students did not show up
結果學生都不出現
The idea of ​​brain degeneration
對於大腦的退化這個觀念
Hope it might be
希望屬裡面可能要
Take a little effort to promote
花一點精神來推廣
lest it be said that the burden will be heavier
免得到說這個負擔會更重
Caused by degeneration of the brain
因為腦的退化才造成
Degeneration of the body thank you
身體的退化謝謝
Thanks
謝謝
As for
至於
cerebral
腦的
rehabilitation for this memory
腹建對於這個記憶
I think
我想
Of course it's not me
當然這不是我
I am professional
我專業
i thought i would ask more
我想我會多請教一下
the expert
這個專家
then think again
然後再來想思考
see how to do it in this direction
看看這個方向怎麼樣做
Thanks
謝謝
Su Chang, I think my question may not have a direct concept with what you just said
苏长 我想我的问题可能跟您刚刚讲的没有直接的观念
But you're an expert on old founders
但是您是老创商的专家
I also want to hear your opinion
我还想听听您的看法
We often see reports abroad
我们常常看到国外有报道
Some people wake up suddenly after being in a coma for many years
有的人在昏迷了好多年以后突然清醒
What is the reason for being sober?
照那种清醒的原因是什么
The other is that these people, after waking up,
另外一个就是说这些人在清醒之后
Has his brain function fully recovered?
他的脑的功能是不是完全恢复了
Or because a certain part will definitely suffer some damage
还是由于某一部分一定会受到一些伤害
yes thank you
对 谢谢
in my experience
在我的经验里面
In fact, quite a few recovered
事实上恢复过来的比例还不少
Even some hypoxic patients
甚至有些缺氧的病人
Well, after half a year and a year, he's fine again.
那么过了半年一年他又很好
But the barriers to function are huge
但是功能的障碍很大
Some hands and feet are not good
有些手脚不行
But some hands and feet are good but he has almost no memory
但有些手脚好但是他几乎没什么记忆功能
Well, it's better. I've seen it too.
那么比较好的我也看过
There is a patient who wakes up six months a year
有一個病人一年六個月醒過來
And there are no obstacles
而且沒有什麼障礙的也有
Of course, I think this is mostly a reward function.
這個當然我想多半是一個帶賞功能
less likely to regenerate
再生的可能性很少
then this is a
那麼這是一個
I'm a photo studio
我這個是一個照相館的
I have been around for so long, I have only experienced one year and six months
我大概這麼久我只經歷過一個一年六個月
A child in a photo studio
一個照相館的一個小孩
a couple
一個夫婦
take good care of this kid
非常照顧這個小孩
every day is like
天天都像
I'll tell a story by the way
我順便講一個故事
this
這個
A good man talks to him every day like this
好人這樣天天跟他講話
how about him
跟他怎麼樣
take care of him fearlessly
照顧他無畏不止
Every day every two weeks for three weeks
每天每個兩個禮拜三個禮拜
Or look at taking medicine or something like that
還是那一看拿藥什麼這些
Then I remember he told me
那麼我就記得他跟我講說
When he woke up at twenty-four
他二十四醒過來的時候
after waking up
醒過來以後
It's getting better and better in a few days
過幾天越來越好越來越好
he asked him
他就問他說
Back of CAM
CAM裏
That's the one
就是那個
Call that CAM again
都又打那個CAM裏
It seems to be from 2008, I will talk about it later
好像是2008的 今後我再講一下
It was expensive when he saw it. At that time, it was tens of thousands of 1.6 million
他那看的時候很貴喔 那時候160幾萬
He seems to have about 800,000 yuan left after he wakes up
他好像他醒過來以後剩下大概80幾萬而已
so he told me the story
所以他講這個故事給我聽
There are not many such examples
那有些這種例子還不是很多
No symptoms can be seen like recovered skin
像恢復的肌膚看不出什麼症狀
But most of the time there will be partial recovery of function
但是多半都會有部分的功能恢復
And it will leave some legacy
而且都是會留下一些後遺比較多
I don't know what kind of patients Director Jiang has encountered.
那不曉得蔣主任有什麼碰過什麼病人
There are still cases where the patient wakes up for a long time
就是病人分明很久醒過來的這種例子還是有
Usually people are everywhere
平時人到處都有
But after waking up
但是恢復醒過來以後
No matter how well his brain functions, it can be explained.
他的腦子功能再怎麼樣是可以解釋的
In fact the whole brain functions like a specialty kyogen
事實上整個腦子功能就像個特產狂言
It means that every member of the troupe must sing well
就是每一個這個團員都要唱得很好的話
So we're honestly a whole function
所以我們老實說我們是一個整個性的功能
So when our honestly functioning cells
所以當我們老實可以運作的細胞
More often it is our husband's chance
越多的時候就是我們老公的機會
When missing basically his
當缺少的時候基本上他的
He may look like you can see through
他也許外表看你能看得過去
when you give him some tests
當你給他一些測試的時候
also found that we can't do it
也發現我們做不起來
The most common is memory
那比較最常見的就是記憶力
just tell him this
就是給他講這個
had breakfast
早餐吃了
Special finished his lunch with two breakfasts once
特別吃完了他中午有兩個早餐的一次
He can't afford it every season
他每一季都請不下
I have to remember the memory that exists or give me a season
就得記憶存在的記憶還是給我一季
probably like this memory
大概是這樣記憶
That is to say, his husband can't
也就是說他老公沒辦法
I can't keep up with everything for you
跟不到給你一切的事
Thanks
謝謝
now purser sorry
現在事務長對不起
because I'm sorry I didn't see you that
因為很抱歉我沒有看到你那個
2007 should come
2007年該來
then i was thinking
那我在想說
How long is the best time for this patient to arrive at the hospital
這個病人到醫院最好是多久
to be sent to the hospital
要送到醫院
that future
那將來
future words
將來以後的話
i won't please
我不會請
Of course it is the biggest job outside of God
當然是神外最大的一個工作
But in the future, can the beef be regenerated?
可是將來那個牛肉能不能說再生
Or is there some drug that can regenerate it
或是有什麼藥物能夠使它再生
Because the whole thing looks like a neuropathy
因為整個看起來是神經病
It should be that symptom, probably a beef problem.
應該是那個症狀大概是牛肉的問題
Is there any better medicine?
有沒有什麼藥物比較好的
at present
目前
So far there has been no major breakthrough
到目前為止都還沒有很大的突破
Including Stem Cells
包括Stem Cell
someone put it in the brain
有人把它中到Brain
How about it
怎麼樣
haven't had a big breakthrough yet.
都還沒有很大的突破
But there are constant heart medicine coming out
不過有不斷的心藥出來
That is to help some metabolism
那有些是幫忙一些代謝
or how
或怎麼樣
But the real regeneration is not so much
但是真正的regeneration的不是那麼多
This still has to work hard
這個還是要努力
Stem Cell is in the animal seems to have some help
Stem Cell是在動物好像有一些幫忙
But if you really use it on people
可是你要真的用到人身上
not necessarily
就不一定
This is too complicated
這個等等複雜度太高了
Environmental factors have too much influence
環境的因素影響太大
Yes, this practice certainly has
對 這個實踐當然是有
But everyone always try their best
不過總是大家都想盡一些辦法
Really see regeneration in people
真正看到人身上regeneration的
not too that
還不是太那個
Thanks
謝謝
Yoon-hyun and then sell the two girls, please.
允賢 然後再賣兩位小姐好不好 來 請
I would like to ask, that is usually after our limbs are severed
我想請問一下喔 那個一般我們手腳斷掉之後
If you want to untie it back, what can't you do after your brain is broken?
要解回去 那有什麼腦摔碎之後 不能
Then I want to ask, that is, assuming that our brain
然後我還想要問一下說 就是假設說我們腦
That is, a certain part, for example, was cut off
就是有某一部分比如說被削掉
It's the part of the brain that's been cut off.
就是被削掉那一部分的腦
Then what will its original function be?
那它原本的功能會是怎麼辦
It's the one we were talking about
它就是 就剛我們在講的那個
Is there any connectivity? This place we sometimes
connectivity有沒有 這個地方我們有時候
During the operation, the pressure on the brain was too high, the dry breath just mentioned
開刀的時候 因為腦壓力太高 剛才講那個 dry breath
dry mask
乾面膜
When you squeeze me out, there is no way to eliminate some of the less important places
把我擠出來的時候沒辦法就把一部分的比較不重要的地方消掉
This karma will also erase it
這個略業也會把它消掉
Where does it go after disappearing?
消掉以後它跑到哪裡?
run to the other side run to other places
跑到對側跑到其他地方去
it comes with a reward
它用帶賞的
A lot of the brain's function is to help that person live in other places.
很多的腦的功能是別的地方在幫那個人過
Just like the choir he mentioned here
就像這邊剛才他講的合唱團
That white gull token is broken
那個白鷗令壞掉了
in the end please go on
就終極請接上去
Of course, the function is not as good as before
功能當然沒有原來那麼好
But what about this
不過呢這個
it always brings rewards
它總是會帶賞過來
no way
沒有辦法
There is no way to connect the Sino-Soviet nerve until now
中蘇神經到現在都沒有辦法接回去
studied for a long time
研究了很久
if this can be regenerated
如果這個能夠再生的話
become the Norbert winner
就變成Norbert得主了
This problem is the Sino-Soviet nerve
這個問題就是中蘇神經
it is mainly missing a
它主要是缺一個
Original Dental Site
Original Dental Site
then what
還是什麼
do not know
不曉得
i forgot now
我現在忘掉了
probably so far
大概到目前為止
There is no way for the central nervous system
中宿神經是沒有辦法
Regenerate
再生的
But when he gets around, he can
但是到了周邊他又可以
He can regenerate after denervation
從神經解以後他就可以再生
The question is, the lady in front
問題來 前面這一位小姐
Thanks
謝謝
Director thank you for protecting young people
署長謝謝你對年輕人的保護
Afterwards I was just listening to the director strict barrier
之後我剛剛在聽署長嚴障
There are references to the brain
裡面有提到有關腦部
Part of the biomarker
biomarker的部分
i feel very interested
我覺得滿有興趣
so i want to know say
所以我想知道說
Can biomarkers become
biomarker是否可以成為
Determining patients with cerebral arterial flow
決定腦動脈流病人
An indicator of the need for surgery
是否需要開刀的一種指標
good question
這個問題很好
Cerebral arterial flow is like this
腦動脈流是這樣
If cerebral arterial flow is usually
如果腦動脈流通常是
It doesn't have to be broken before everyone will show symptoms.
不一定會破掉以後大家才會症狀出來
What about some that you are talking about are not broken?
那有些呢你現在講的是沒有破掉的
suddenly discovered
突然發現的
Then probably quite a high percentage have found this
那麼大概也蠻高的比例有發現這個
about a few percent
大概幾個percent有
one to three or so
一到三左右
Sometimes this arterial flow is found in routine examinations
有時候在例行的檢查裡面會發現這個動脈流
Then do you want to go under the knife?
那到底要不要去開刀
some smaller
有些比較小的
sometimes or never broken
有時候或者是從來沒有破過的
or in a more dangerous place
或者在比較危險的地方的
Sometimes we don't advocate surgery
有時候我們不主張開刀
Well BioMarker has no way of knowing that
那麼BioMarker沒有辦法知道那個
Because generally unless that arterial flow has been pressed to some brain
因為一般除非那個動脈流已經壓到一些腦部
The brain releases abnormal markers due to injury
那腦部因為受傷而釋放出不正常的Marker
He just needs to go under the knife
他才需要去開刀
Only then did I know if he was under pressure and the pressure was crushed to the brain
才知道說他有沒有壓力壓力壓破到腦部
If it's very small arterial flow probably not
如果是很小的動脈流大概不會
not easy to find
不容易找出來
that if big
那如果很大的
he can see
他可以看得出來
I think
我想
The development of BioMaker is
BioMaker的發展是
a hope for the future
未來的一個希望
so probably
所以大概
Many people are looking for this thing now
現在很多人都在找這個東西
See if you can actually do some
看看真正能不能做一些
that's like this brigade lake
那像這個旅湖
average travel lake
一般的旅湖
Do you know what arterial flow means?
大家知道動脈流的意思嗎
arterial flow is not flow
動脈流不是流
arterial flow is a
動脈流是一個
where the blood vessels cross
這個血管交叉的地方
there is a weakness here
這裡有一個弱點
it sticks out
它就突出一塊來
highlight a little
突出一個小小的
But at the age of
但是到了一貫年齡的時候
it breaks
它就碰破掉
Broken brain hemorrhage
破掉了腦出血就
can't save
救不回來
or
或者是
go in and clip it off
要進去把它夾掉
cut it off
開刀把它夾掉
that some arterial flow
那有些動脈流
before it broke
就還沒破以前
It's on a routine MRI
它就在例行的MRI
Or CT scan found
或者CT scan檢查就發現
that's what we just did
那就是我們剛才
This is located in the proposed
這位於是所提出
made by miss
小姐所提出來的
Are you going to clamp it off?
到底要不要去把它夾掉
very
就很
fee this
費這個
Dime gold
毫金的
This is for clinical use
這個是用臨床來幫
Probably Meyermag didn't help on this one
可能邁爾馬格在這一方面沒有幫忙
I'm sorry, may I ask Su Chang
對不起 請問一下素長
If say after your brain contusion
如果說你的腦磋傷之後
after surgery
開了刀之後
A piece of your skull is missing
你的頭蓋骨不見了一塊
Will that affect the whole
那個會不會影響到整個的
Won't
不會
Will he
那他會不會
His brain injury is more important
他腦的受傷比較重要
Brain injury is more important
腦的受傷比較重要
Will it affect your optic nerve?
那他會不會影響你的視神經
optic nerve
視神經跟隱蔑神經
that depends on the location
那個要看位置
If the optic nerve goes this way
視神經從這邊走的話
If you are affecting sometimes
如果你在影響到有時候會
will affect
會影響到
some people will affect
有些人會影響到
look at the location
看位置
What if it affects the future?
那如果影響到之後呢
what will happen
會怎麼樣
Okay, let me talk about the bones first.
好 我先講骨頭
bone
骨頭
bone defect
骨頭這個缺損
often see
常常看到
because for the time
因為為了當時
I was talking about the dry bread just now
我剛才是講說剛才那個乾麵包
squeezed out
擠出來了
So when you need to save your life
所以你要趕快救命的時候
put the bones
把骨頭
let go of the bones
骨頭先暫時放掉
put it up
放起來
that's okay
那個沒有關係
It will collapse badly for patients in the future
對病人將來會塌得很厲害
You can even raise a bird here
甚至這裡都可以養一隻小鳥
so big
那麼大
but it won't happen
但是呢 不會怎麼樣
will not affect the patient
對病人不會有影響
That's progress now
那現在也很進步
Now it is even possible to use a computer to defend
現在甚至可以用電腦衛塗
Do this arc and everything well
把這個弧度啊什麼都做好
and then put it in
然後再裝進去
Dress up exactly like you used to
裝得跟你原來一模一樣
Of course it's best if your own bones are the best
那當然最好是自己的骨頭是最好
But now it can be done well
不過現在可以做得很好
so don't worry about this
所以這個不用擔心
What about your second question?
那你剛剛第二個是什麼問題
I suddenly can't think
我突然想不及
Will it affect the four nerves?
它會不會影響到四神經
maybe a nerve
也許是神經
Yes, this is the position where you will be injured.
是 這個就要受傷的位置
facial nerve words
顏面神經的話
Sometimes the path of its facial nerve is injured
有時候它的顏面神經的經路受傷的話
That face is crooked
那臉就歪掉了
Then the four nerve pathways will be crooked if injured.
那麼四神經經路受傷也會歪掉
also can't see
也會看不到
So it all depends on the location of the injury.
所以這個都看受傷的位置而定
What if it only affects
那如果只是影響到的話呢
affected
影響到就
For example, let's see why
譬如說看是什麼原因
The facial nerve because it is not the Sino-Soviet nerve
顏面神經因為它不是中蘇神經
So some can be used
所以有些可以用接的
but very difficult
但是非常困難
The regeneration rate is not necessarily high
再生的比例也不一定很高
Four nerves are more difficult
四神經就比較困難
Four nerves if it is because
四神經如果它是因為
Fractures compress this to sometimes decompress it from the bone
骨折把這個壓到有時候從骨頭把它解壓
it recovers some
它會恢復一些
in place of the four nerve tubes
在四神經管的地方
Often there will be a fracture in this place that presses it
常常會有這個地方骨折壓到它
there is hope for that
那個就有希望
But it may not be able to recover much
但是也不一定能夠恢復多少
here's a question leave
這邊有一個問題請假
hello secretary
書長你好
I now have a medical
我現在有一個醫學的
I want to ask you about the actual case
實際案例要請教你
OK
好不好
The first is to say
第一個就是說
In October 1999
在民國99年10月的時候
that is
就是
Four knots when driving
開車的時候就產生四節
One car becomes two or three
一台汽車變成兩三台
Later, I went to take a radiography
後來去照慈禁造影
Underwater tumors found under the brain
發現腦下水底腫瘤
Later, it was surgery with a small Weijing pen gun.
後來就是用小維境筆槍的手術
had surgery
去動過手術
Hospitalized for about ten days
住院差不多十天左右
It's been almost a year and a half now
現在已經差不多一年半了
Follow up every six months
半年有追蹤一次
Now tracking and found another problem is in
現在追蹤又發現一個問題就是在
Where the blood vessels grow again
血管的地方又長出來了
but after outpatient
但在門診以後
It's now going to be treated with a type of radiation
它現在是要用一種放射治療
because in the blood vessels
因為在血管的地方
there's no way to do it again
沒有辦法再開刀
This symptom is what the director just mentioned
這個症狀就是剛剛署長所講過的
just dizzy
就是有會頭暈
headaches sleep disturbances energy disturbances
頭痛 睡眠的障礙 機力的障礙
There is one more serious
還有一項更嚴重的就是
emotionally unstable
情緒很不穩定
a good day a bad day
一天很好 一天很差
Now if the machine tracks
現在機器追蹤的話
It uses a method called radiation
它要用一種叫做放射
radiation therapy
放射治療
Radiation therapy I further understand is to use
放射治療我進一步了解是用著
Noni knife
諾麗刀
It's right to treat with a Noni knife
諾麗刀去治療就對了
Then I want to ask the Commissioner
那我要請問署長說
This noni knife treatment will have
這個諾麗刀治療以後會有
What are the side effects?
會有什麼後遺症
Thanks
謝謝
By the way, let me tell you about the pituitary gland
順便跟大家講一聲腦下垂體
The pituitary gland flow is quite special
腦下垂體流是蠻特別的
it grows in the center of the brain
它是長在腦的中央
pituitary fossa
腦下垂體窩
grow out of that
從那底下長出來
grow one
長出來一個
The biggest one is that it affects just
最大一個就是它影響剛好在
it's just under that forty gold cross
它剛好在那個四成金的交叉的下面
so when it gets up
所以它起來的時候
The first one goes to the top of the four-cross
第一個就頂到四交叉
what would a quadruple cross cause
四交叉就會造成什麼
two sided horses
兩外側偏馬
Now suddenly you feel that this person often has this
現在突然你會覺得這個人常常有這個
I wonder why this person suddenly became so proud
就會覺得說這個人怎麼突然變得這麼驕傲
I'm not happy with this big hello
我這個大招呼都不快
Because he can't see clearly on either side of the outside.
因為他兩邊外側都看不太清楚
so sometimes you don't know you're driving
所以有時候你自己不知道你開車
easy to change pressure to get
容易變壓去弄到
Someone gets you on the walk and you don't even know
有人在走路上弄到你也不知道
So when you walk, you will meet this edge
所以走路的時候這個邊邊都會碰到
because he can't see
因為這邊他看不到
So he pressed from the optic chiasm
所以他從視交叉的地方壓到了
so he will
所以他會這樣
So after the surgery
所以開完刀以後
He's such a cute question
他這個有些撐萌的問題
I think your symptoms should be fine.
我想大概你那個症狀應該都很好吧
Those who are cute are good
撐萌那些都很好
is very stable now
現在是很穩定
but he said it makes sense
但是他說有意義
I know
我知道
This is because he might be on the alarm cat
這個因為他可能在警動貓有的上面
stick on it
黏在上面
It is risky to stick to it and then take it
黏在上面再去拿就有風險
use that noni knife
用那個諾麗刀
We call it radiosurgery
我們叫做放射手術
It is different from radiation therapy
它是跟放射治療又不一樣
Radiation therapy is just radiation that
放射治療只是放射那個
The radiology surgery is inside the computer.
那放射手術就在電腦裡面
it's only a little bit
它只有一點點
but it's pretty accurate
但是它算得很精準
It turns front and back, left and right
它把前後左右啊什麼
Any distance can be calculated
什麼距離都能算出來
it follows that place
它就照著那個地方
all the light is concentrated there
所有的光線都集中在那裡
burn that bit
就把那一點燒掉
what about this
那這個呢
It's like putting that point
等於是把那一點呢
destroy the whole
整個破壞掉
brain damage
腦子破壞
But it has little chance of injuring surrounding tissue
但是它傷害到周圍組織的機會很小
But there are also a few
但是也有少數會碰到
so still
所以還是
of course there is a chance
當然有機會有
but rarely
但是很少
because it is very accurate
因為它非常準
So I guess this way is right
所以我想這個方式是對的
that if you open it again
那個如果再去開它
sometimes that
有時候那個
What if the arteries lose blood?
萬一緊動脈失血啦
or how suddenly broke
或怎麼樣突然破掉啦
That's dangerous too
那這個就也是很危險
I think the doctor was very right in judging
我想那個醫生是非常正確的判斷
Come, Director Liang
來 梁主任
I think because of time
我想因為時間的關係
probably the last question
大概是最後一個問題
OK
好不好
OK I want to ask a fact
OK 我想問一個事實上
It's a practical question
是很實務上的問題
Although the dean Cheng Wu just said that
雖然剛才那個成務院長已經講過說
Director for promoting this
署長因為推動這個
relationship with security
帶安全罵的關係
Saved 3,000 lives a year
救了 每年救了三千條命
but in fact
但是事實上
This affects other
這個會影響到其他的
The Business of a Brain Surgeon
腦外科醫師的生意
so i want to ask
所以我想請問一下
have you ever been scolded or
你有沒有被罵過還是這樣
I was surprised to say
我很吃驚的就是說
we used to be surgeons
我們曾經外科醫生
everyone is very loving
大家都非常有愛心
so i was surprised
所以我很查吃驚
When it was promoted in Taipei City for the first time
那個第一次在台北市推動的時候
Ward suddenly reduced by one-third
病房突然少掉三分之一
I don't see anyone complaining
我看沒有人抱怨
when the second push
那第二次推的時候
that's even worse
那更慘
Because like many young physicians
因為像很多年輕醫師
It's all based on this night
都是靠著這個晚上開刀
life in these emergency rooms
這些急診過日子
suddenly gone
突然都沒了
It suddenly disappeared. It turned out to be a five-day knife in a week.
突然沒了,原來是一個禮拜開五天刀
less than one a week
一個禮拜不到一個
Taipei City in particular fell very fast
台北市尤其掉得很快
But everyone is very used to it and thinks that saying this
但是大家就很習慣,覺得說這個
Including me, I don't think anyone opens these, and if it's safe to scold my brother, no one should open them
包括我在內,我覺得這些都沒人開,覺得安全罵弟弟也就應該沒人開
But he just can't do it like this, so fortunately no one complained, but a group complained
但是他就是這樣不行,所以還好沒有沒有什麼人抱怨,倒是有一個團體抱怨
keep learning, keep learning
一直學會,一直器官一直學會
No, all of a sudden, there were five or six hundred in a month, and suddenly there were two or three hundred left
沒有突然沒有了,一個月有五六百個,突然變到剩下兩三百個
less car accidents
因為車禍少了
This is another discovery, that
這個是另外一個發現,那
God's other star, no one complains
神另外一顆沒有人抱怨
i admire them
我很敬佩他們
Thanks
謝謝
I'm here to thank you very very much
我在這裡要非常非常感謝
Thank you very much Director
非常謝謝署長
If it wasn't for the director
如果不是當初署長
you advocate hard hats
你提倡安全帽
I could maybe 10 years ago
我可能或許10年前
I will become a professional
我就變成職務人了
really thank you very much
真的非常的感謝
I think the director is blessed
我想署長造福了
all taxi groups
所有的計車組
Thanks
謝謝
our speech today
我們今天的演講
come to apply
來到申請
this time we
我們這一次
Thank you Director for giving us a new speech
謝謝署長給我們新台演講
Thank you also for the people
也謝謝他為全民
Contribution of working with him
跟他合作的貢獻